music
music
applause
applause
come friends
來的朋友
Then I'm here on behalf of Academia Sinica
那我在這裡代表中央研究院
Welcome to our feast of knowledge today
歡迎大家來參加我們今天的知識饗宴
Our keynote speaker today is
我們今天的主講人是
Chen Yihao, a research fellow of the Institute of Statistical Science of our school
本院統計科學研究所的陳奕豪研究員
What about Dr. Chen?
那陳博士呢是
is a research fellow at our Institute of Statistics
是在統計我們的統計所的研究員
National Yang Ming University Institute of Public Health
也是國立陽明大學公共衛生研究所
and the Peace of the Department of Mathematics, National Taiwan Normal University
以及國立臺灣師範大學數學系的和平
and adjunct professor
及兼任教授
Dr. Chen graduated from the Electrical Engineering Department of National Taiwan University with a bachelor's degree
陳博士是在臺大的電機系畢業的學士
Then his experience is a bit special
然後他的這個經歷有點特殊
He later went to the statistics office of the town university
他後來去了鎮大的統計所
got a master's degree
拿了碩士學位
Later, I went to National Taiwan University Institute of Public Health
後來到臺大公共衛生研究所
Ph.D.
拿的博士學位
We can see this development of it
我們可以看到它的這個發展
How to go from motor to statistics
怎麼從電機走到統計
Then I went to the guard's side
然後又走到公衛裡頭這邊
with this
跟這個
What did you tell us today?
今天跟我們講的呢
Earthquake risk again
又是地震風險
so this
所以這個
We can see that this statistic
我們可以知道看到說這個統計
can contain many, many
是可以包含很多很多的
different facets of science
不同面向的科學
then he is
那他在
in the past served
在曾經擔任過
Assistant Professor of Mathematics Department of Normal University
師範大學數學系的助理教授
When he was in 2000
他在2000年的時候
Entered the Institute of Statistical Science, Academia Sinica
進入了中央研究院統計科學研究所工作
It's been 18 years now
到現在已經18年了
that he was
那他曾經
what is his research interest
他的研究興趣呢
in statistical methodology
是在統計方法學
Biostatistics etc.
生物統計等等
the nearest research center
那最近的研究中心
is in survival data analysis
是在存活數據分析
we can all listen
我們大家可以聽一下
Analysis of long-term follow-up data
長期追蹤數據的分析
Big Data Database Diagnosis
大數據資料庫診
and analyze incomplete data analysis
和分析不完整數據分析
It sounds like it's all data analysis
這樣聽起來好像都是數據分析
But it is divided into many aspects
可是又分了很多很多的面向
Well, he's done an excellent job of research.
那他的研究工作做得非常出色
He has won the National Science Council
他曾經得過國科會
Mr. Wu Dayu Memorial Award of the current Ministry of Education and Technology
現在的教育科技部的吳大尤先生紀念獎
This is for young researchers
這是為了年輕的研究人員
The teacher spoke very smoothly
老師特別順利的講
And then when you're a bit more senior
然後當你比較資深一點的話
There's another one called the Distinguished Research Award
另外有一個叫做傑出研究獎
Then Mr. Chen also won this research award.
那陳老師也得過這個研究獎
Then also won the Research Assistant Award for Young Scholars from the China Security Research Institute
然後也得過中安研究院的年輕學者研究助作獎
He also recently supported a deep root project in the courtyard
他最近還有一個深根計畫在院裡頭支持
So his researcher is in our younger generation
所以他的研究師在我們年輕一代
Or when it comes to the tenured generation, it is a very outstanding one
或者到了終生代是相當出色的一位
So today his topic we see here is
那今天他的題目我們看到這邊是
Integrative analysis of seismic risk assessment and different databases
以地震風險評估與不同資料庫的整合分析
Analysis as an example to tell everyone
分析为例 要告诉大家
what statistics do
统计学在做些什么
The first will talk about two practical examples
第一个会讲两个实际的例子
The first example is statistical methods and techniques
第一个例子是统计学的方法与技术
These introduce some
这一些介绍一些
some in statistics
在统计学上的一些
those technologies here
的那些技术这边
then will
然后会
Use this more than 7,000 pens for Taiwan earthquake
用这个7000多笔台湾地震
Surface Acceleration Data
地表加速的资料
Established a model for earthquake risk assessment
建立起地震风险评估的模型
Very useful for earthquake engineers
对地震工程学家是非常有用的
So we can see that the statistical
所以我们可以看出统计的
tools in discipline
纪律学中的工具
how do we use it
我们要怎么去用它
Then according to the content and characteristics of the seismic survey data
然后依据地震测证的资料的内含跟特性
How to find these commonalities
怎么去找出这些共通性
Error and Uncertainty of Velocity Data
速度资料的误差跟不确定性
Of course, what we want most is to be able to accurately predict
那当然我们最想的是能够精确的预测
These
这些
These surface accelerations and the risk of earthquakes
這些地表加速度跟地震的風險
can make a good assessment
可以做一個很好的評估
so where should i live
所以應該住在哪裡
Or maybe we can listen to it today
或是我們今天大概可以聽了以後
Can you tell which places in Taiwan are safer?
可以知道說台灣什麼地方會比較安全
Then the second example is to use introductory statistics
然後第二個例子是要用介紹統計學
How can we, in our current era of so-called big data
如何在目前我們所謂的大數據的時代中
Can be combined with many of the increasingly popular
可以結合現在很多日益普及
There are also a large number of electronic databases
還有大量的電子數據資料庫
So from these databases you can
所以可以從這些資料庫裡面
Long and short
節長補短
Then we need to sort out accurate and useful information
然後再要整理出精確有用的訊息
So this is the second question
所以這是第二個題目
Integrated analysis of different databases
不同資料庫的整合分析
So now we have a lot of databases in Taiwan
所以我們現在台灣有很多的資料庫
We have a database of health insurance
我們有健保的資料庫
and the National Health Interview Survey database
還有國民健康訪問調查的資料庫
Just use this as an example
就用這個做例子
Then use the large amount of statistical probability above
然後利用統計機率學上面的大量
So to explore the relationship between some diseases
所以探討說一些疾病之間的關聯
For example, in medicine, there is a difference between a banded foam pillow and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.
譬如說醫學中帶狀泡枕跟慢性阻塞性肺病之間
There is still some connection
居然還有一些關聯
So this is why I said that even if it is not a scientist in medicine
所以這個所以我說即使不是這個在醫學上面的科學家
Then we start from this seemingly abstract and somewhat cold statistics
那我們從這種好像很抽象有點冰冷的統計學
But we thought we could make some connections
可是我們覺得我們可以做下一些連結
So today we are very happy to have our speaker Chen Yihao
所以今天很高興我們請到了我們今天的主講人陳毅豪
Researchers come to tell us what statistics are doing
研究員來告訴我們統計學在做些什麼
Now please welcome our keynote speaker today with warm applause
現在請大家以熱烈掌聲歡迎我們今天的主講人
Well, thank you very much for the invitation and introduction from the head of the seat
好非常謝謝座府院長的邀請還有介紹
Thank you very much for participating in our variety show
也非常謝謝大家參加我們綜演的節目
This is the experience activity of each college
每個學院的這個就是享驗的活動
Everyone has a day's work
大家上了一天的班
or a day of class
或者是上了一天的課
And then stay here at night
然後晚上還要在這邊
Thank you all
非常感謝大家
That
那
Vice President Zhou just introduced
剛剛周副院長已經介紹
Let me introduce to you very clearly what I want to talk about today.
給大家介紹很清楚我今天要講的內容
That
那
That's because I, as a
那因為我作為一個
statistics this
統計學的這個
In this study of statistics
在統計學的這個研究方面
I also
我也
Experienced
經歷了
If you start counting from the doctoral dissertation
如果從做博士論文開始算的話
It's been more than 20 years
已經經歷了超過20年了
so i think
所以我想
if i want to be here today
我今天如果要在
Just enjoy what to say
只是享驗講什麼東西的話
I can probably only say
我大概也只能講
topic like this
像這樣的題目了
just to let everyone know
就是讓大家知道就是說
In the end statistics
到底統計學
These read statistics
這些念統計的
what the hell are they doing
到底他們在做一些什麼
because doing may have
因為在做可能有
many must
許多人必須
It is not common for people who have the opportunity to come into contact with statistics
並不是平常有機會會接觸到統計學的
The background of this picture is the Statistics Institute of Academia Sinica
這個畫面的背景就是我們中研院統計所
is where I work
就是我工作的地方
In fact, it is directly opposite the Academic Activity Center
其實它就在學術活動中心的正對面
past this lawn
這個草坪過去
So if you are free, you are welcome to do it.
所以有空的話歡迎大家來做做
good
好
That
那
So at the beginning, I will briefly introduce some background of statistics.
所以一開始我就先很大概的介紹一下統計學的一些背景
The English of statistics is this statistics
統計學它的英文是這個statistice
That word actually evolved from the word state.
那這個字其實是從state這個字演變過來的
that state we know its
那state我們知道它的
it means country
它的意思就是國家的意思
so
所以
Indeed, statistics
的確當初統計學
Its main job is to
它的主要的工作就是
the government or ruler of a country
一個國家的政府或是統治者
In order to understand some of the current situation in his country
他為了要了解他國家的一些現況
For example, the population
譬如說人口數啊
then this
然後這個
How much is this income?
有多少的這個收入啊
How many agricultural products are there?
有多少的農產品啊
How many cows and how many sheep?
有多少頭牛多少頭羊這樣的
hope to have these numbers
希望有這些數字
what about the government
這個政府呢
Hope to have these numbers
希望有這些數字出來
So what about statistics at that time?
所以統計那個時候的統計學呢
is doing something like this
就是在做這樣的事情
So it’s actually equivalent to what we’re talking about today.
所以其實就是相當於今天我們講的
government statistics
政府統計
just like us today
也就像我們今天
like us in taiwan
像在台灣我們這些
Government agency host office
政府機構主機處啊
The Statistics Office of the Ministry of Economic Affairs and the Ministry of Health and Welfare
這些經濟部啊衛生福利部的統計處
what they are doing
他們在做的事情
is very similar to
是非常類似的
What about the statistics at that time?
那當時的統計學呢
Because the data at that time
因為當時的數據呢
Mainly probably because at the time
主要都是可能是因為當時
The amount of data at that time was not as large and complex as it is today
當時的數據量還不會像到今天這麼大這麼複雜
So in fact, the data at that time were mainly obtained through censuses.
所以其實當時的數據其實主要都是通過普查得到的
That is, the entire country has been investigated
就是所有整個國家都調查了
So the main work of statistics at this time
所以統計學在這個時候所做的主要的工作
In fact, it is to do the so-called data summary
其實就是做所謂的data summary
It is the work of summarizing the data
就是把數據做一些摘要整理的工作
It's like when we were young, we were in elementary or middle school
那就像我們小時候我們在小學或者是中學
A little basic statistics we learned
我們學到的一點基礎的統計
We are doing this so-called data summary, right?
我們就是在做這種所謂的data summary對不對
For example, we might count
譬如說我們可能會算
Let's be honest and ask us to calculate an average of some data
老實說會叫我們算一個一些數據的平均數
Calculate the median of some data
算一些數據的中位數
the standard deviation of the data
數據的標準差這一類的
then this is
那這個就是
The so-called Data Summary
所謂的Data Summary
Summary's Testase
Summary's Testase
is to put the original many numbers
就是把本來很多數字的
many numbers
很多數字
we may not have time to see it
我們可能沒有時間去看它
Or don't want to see it at all
或者說根本不想去看它
but we put it
但是我們把它
only minus
僅減
Digest it into a few important numbers
把它摘要成幾個重要的數字
Through these simple numbers
透過這幾個簡單的數字
we can understand this
我們就可以了解這個
thousands of data
成千上萬筆數據的
general picture
大致的全貌
we can understand it inside
我們就可以了解它裡面
contains the message
所含有的訊息
good
好
So actually
所以其實
what about this thing
這個東西呢
maybe look say
也許看起來說
This is before the 19th century
這個是19世紀前的
maybe
也許是
Um
嗯
very traditional
非常傳統的
or very
或者是說非常
maybe very boring
也許是非常無趣的
like when we were kids
就像我們小時候在
Although the average
雖然平均數一樣
it's just a process
它只是一個工序
but behind it
可是它背後呢
actually
其實
There is also a very important statistical theory
也是有很重要的統計理論的
that is
就是說
it rises
它起息
Adequacy of our statistical theory
我們統計理論講的充分性
That is to say, how do you use a few simple
就是說你怎麼樣用幾個簡單
very few numbers
非常少數的幾個數字
will be able to grasp thousands of
就能夠掌握到成千上萬的
Especially when it comes to big data
尤其現在講大數據
so much data
這麼多的數據
when you have no way to see it
你根本沒有辦法去看它的時候
Through a few data
透過少數幾個數據
to be able to summarize the key points
就能夠摘要出其中的重點
information in it
其中的information
That thing is actually
那這個東西其實是
In our statistical theory
我們統計理論當中
very important so-called sufficiency
非常重要的 所謂充分性
sufficient statistics
充分統計量
sufficient statistic
sufficient statistic
such a concept
這樣的概念
then next
那麼在接下來
after the 19th century
在19世紀之後
Statistics began to develop differently
統計學開始有了不一樣的發展
We call it modern statistic
我們稱它為modern statistic
at this time
那這個時候
mainly depends on
主要是有賴於
At this time, the incentives developed by Bloomberg
這個時候也在彭博發展的這個激勵
Probability. We learned a little about probability when we were kids, right?
機率學 我們小時候學過一點機率學對不對
There is a little chance of losing Size
丟Size出現一點的機率
One in six is ​​a probability, right?
六分之一這種機率學對不對
That
那
Because of the tools of probability
因為有了機率學的這樣的工具呢
Then our Institute of Statistics and Probability
那我們統計學利用機率學所
What about some tools developed?
發展出來的一些工具呢
At this time, the focus of statistics
這個時候統計學的這個關注的
The point is never just what I just said
重點就從不再只是剛剛講的
census data
普查的數據了
What about the data we care about now?
那現在所關心的數據呢
also includes the so-called
也包含了所謂
Sampling
現在我們常常聽到的抽樣
right
對不對
The data obtained by sampling
抽樣所得到的數據
Then use probability
那麼利用機率學
What about some tools developed in probability theory?
機率理論裡面所發展出來的一些工具呢
What about statistics?
那麼統計學呢
Can these tools be used to deal with it?
可以利用這些工具來處理呢
Because of the randomness in the sampled data
因為抽樣所得到的數據當中所帶有的隨機性
randomness
隨機性
I think you can imagine that
我想大家可以想像到就是說
today if we were to
今天如果我們要在
For example, this one at our site
比如說我們現場的這個
Among the audience friends
聽眾朋友當中
Draw these 10 people out
抽這個10個人出來
Of course, there is a lot of randomness in this
這個當然就有很大的隨機性
great uncertainty
很大的不確定性
maybe these people
可能這些人
maybe those people will be selected
可能那些人會被選出來
so
所以
This is what is meant by randomness
所謂的隨機性就是這種意思
how to deal with this
那怎麼樣處理這種
randomness
隨機性
How to deal with this kind of randomness and uncertainty
怎麼樣在這種隨機性不確定性當中
find a pattern
找出一個規律
then this is the time
那這個就是這個時候
A focus of statistics
統計學的一個重點
The tools used are mainly
那用到的工具主要是
tools of probability
機率學上面的工具
So this time statistics
所以這個時候統計學
its main job
它的主要工作
Besides what I just said
也除了這個剛剛講的
What about data summary
data summary之外呢
What about finding the so-called sufficient statistics?
找出所謂的充分統計量之外呢
In addition
另外呢
There is still one
還有一個
The point is what we call statistical inference
重點呢 就是我們稱之為統計推論
statistical inference
statistical inference
Okay, statistical inference, what does statistical inference mean?
好 統計推論 統計推論是什麼意思呢
That is, because our current data
就是說因為我們現在的數據
Probably only a small part of the whole group
很可能只是整個群體當中的一小部分而已
Like we poll, right? We sample
就像我們民意調查對不對 我們抽樣
Objects of these visits sampled by this call
這個打電話所抽樣的這些訪問的對象
Just a small part of the whole group
只是整個群體當中的一小部分而已
But we want to take advantage of this sampled fraction
但是我們希望利用這個所抽樣的一小部分
you can speculate, deduce the whole group's
就可以去推測 去推論整個群體的
a phenomenon a result
一個現象 一個結果
so this is
所以這個是
This so-called modern statistics
這個所謂modern statistics
an important thing to do
所要做的一個重要的
The work of so-called statistical inference
所謂的統計推論的工作
So the purpose is to get out of the sampled samples
所以目的就是希望從抽樣的樣本當中去
guess the larger group behind us
推測我們背後更大的這個群體
The situation of classification or the real situation behind it
類選的情況 或者是背後的真實的情況
So here are two simple examples
所以接下來就舉兩個簡單的例子
That's what I think, everyone may be better than everyone
就是我想這個大家也許是大家比較可以
Expose to examples of statistics that are commonly heard
接觸到平常會聽到統計的例子
Well, this is actually what we call Modern statistics
那這其實也是我們所謂Modern statistics
Now very widely used
現在非常廣泛的應用
One example of this is this poll
那其中一個例子就是這個民意調查
Or an example of what we call statistically confidence intervals
或者我們統計上叫做信賴區間這樣的例子
That passage is actually from this
那這段話其實是從這個
directly on a medium
一個媒體上面直接
Just copied it down, directly copied it up
直接把它抄下了 直接copy上來的
Then this survey is commissioned by a certain organization to a certain polling company
那本次調查為某某機構委託某某民調公司
From March 12th to 15th, 2018
於2018年3月12日至15日
For the north and the north and the region
針對北北及地區
Adults over the age of 64 who fly business jets
居於年滿64歲的成年人進行公務機
A survey of coal-fired power plants was successfully visited
燃煤電廠一件調查 成功訪問
1079 people are below 95% confidence level
1079位民眾在95%信心水準之下
The sampling error is 2.98 percentage points for the government
抽樣誤差為政府2.98個百分點
I think everyone sees this
我想大家看到這樣的這個
When seeing such a text
看到這樣的一個文字的時候
or when you hear something like this
或是聽到這樣一段話的時候
should feel familiar
應該覺得好像滿熟悉的
right
對不對
Because it seems that we can often hear
因為好像我們常常可以聽到
The results of such polls
這樣的民意調查的結果
that is to say
那這邊就是說
Why is there this sampling error
為什麼會有這個抽樣誤差
This government 2.98 percent
這個政府2.98個百分點
This number comes out like this
這樣的這個數字出來
Why is there a 95% confidence level?
為什麼會有95%信心水準
Such numbers come out
這樣的數字出來
In fact, this reflects
其實這個就是反映了
Our current statistics
我們現在的統計學
Not just to understand this 1079-bit sampling sample
不是只是要瞭解這個1079位抽樣樣本
It's just the result
出來的結果而已
In fact, we are more important from these 1079 bits
其實我們更重要的是從這1079位
In this sampled sample
這個抽樣出來的樣本裡面
To estimate in the end Jeonbuk
去推估到底全北北
adults in their area
其地區這些成年人
Their opinions on this public housing and coal-fired power plant
他們對於這個公屋以及燃煤電廠的意見
how is it
是怎麼樣的
Because you have to infer a
因為你要從一個樣本去推測一個
a large group
一個大的群體
It's like you're trying to understand the whole iceberg from the tip
就好像你要從冰山的一角去了解整個冰山
So there will be a little error in this
所以這種是會有一點點誤差的
We have to allow a little error
我們要容許一點誤差存在的
So there will be this sampling error
所以就會有這種抽樣誤差
2.98 percentage points
2.98個百分點
Such numbers run out
這樣的數字跑出來
that is to say
那這邊就是說
I would like to ask those present
想請問一下在座的
Dear friends here
現場在座的各位朋友們
That is, have you noticed this?
就是說 大家有沒有發現這個
The number 1079 and the two numbers 2.98%
1079這個數字跟2.98%這兩個數字
Have you found any connection between them?
有沒有發現他們之間的一點關聯
can we be this
我們可不可以就是這個
I don't know if there are comments
不知道有沒有講評
That is to say, can this
就是說可不可以這個
Give it a shot, but there are statisticians here.
真打一下 不過在座有統計專家了
here are
在座有
A better statistician than me is sitting here
比我更厲害的統計專家坐在這裡
so you can't fight
所以你們不能打
Have you found out whether this 1079 has anything to do with this 2.98%
大家有沒有發現這1079跟這個2.98%有沒有什麼關係
sorry
對不起
3% error
3%的誤差
But this 3% or 2.98% is different from 10
但是這個3%或者說2.98%跟10
79 What's the matter?
79有什麼關係
There is still a mathematical relationship
還是有個數學關係的
right
對
yes it's his
對這是他的
It's him
這是他無差嘛
But he has a definite mathematical formula
但是他有一個明確的數學公式的
right
對
1079 how to get 2.98%
1079怎麼樣得到2.98%的
Do you have a quicker mental calculation?
有沒有心算算得快一點的
that is
就是說
Find out how this 2.98 came from
發現這個2.98是怎麼來的
Where did this error come from?
這個誤差是怎麼來的
Even better, this Vice President Zhou is too smart
更好哇這個周副院長太聰明了
It is indeed better
的確是開更好
It's better to drive and then count down
是開更好然後再倒數
that is
就是
3.4 Yes because there is another 20% off
3.4對因為還要再打個9八折
We have to multiply by 0.98 but usually that 0.98 we just
還要再乘0.98但是通常那個0.98我們就
don't care
可以不管
So it's almost
所以差不多就是
root sign open root sign
根號 開根號
that's what we call statistics
就是我們叫我們統計學
A word we statisticians say most often
我們統計學家最常講的一個字
is the square root n
就是根號n
The root sign n is the number of samples
根號n就是樣本數
So the square root n is in our statistics
所以根號n在我們統計學裡面
is a magic number
是一個神奇數字
root sign n so everyone today
根號n 所以大家今天
you will know
你就知道了
what statisticians do
統計學家做的事情
In fact, it is very simple, it is the root number n
其實很簡單 就是根號n
so later you see this
所以以後你看到這個
When the news is broadcasting the results of this poll again
新聞又在播這個民意調查的結果的時候
When this reporter is still talking
當這個記者還在講
When successfully interviewing 1079 people
成功訪問1079位民眾的時候
you can figure it out right away
你馬上就可以算出
Incorrect sampling is a percentage point sent by the government
抽樣無差是政府寄個百分點
then your child your friend
那你的小孩 你的朋友
must adore you
一定會非常崇拜你
Then the second example is
那第二個例子就是
p-value I want to do it again
p-value 我想再做
If there is this to engage in scientific research
如果有這個從事科學研究
especially this biomedical
特別是這個生物醫學
or social science
或者是社會科學
of this research
這種研究的
Probably very familiar with P-value
大概就非常熟悉P-value
Because I have to follow this P-value all day long
因為整天都要跟這個P-value
deal, right?
打交道對不對
because we basically
因為我們基本上
we do an experiment
我們做一個實驗
we want to see this experiment
我們要看這個實驗
Is it the result of the experiment
是不是實驗的結果
Is it enough to support
是不是足以支持
Results of our experiments
我們實驗的結果
it is indeed a
它的確是一個
a significant result
有顯著性的一個結果的
when shrinking
假縮的時候
Then P-value
那麼P-value
Its size basically reflects the
它的大小基本上是反映了
Such experimental data
這樣的實驗數據
it supports
它支持
Experimental results
實驗結果
did not have this
並沒有這個
full of this salience
充分的這個顯著性
such a contraction
這樣的假縮
so
所以
If the number of this P-value is larger
這個P-value的數字如果越大
If the number of p value is larger
p value 的數字如果越大
For example like this 0.452
譬如說像這個0.452
p value must be connected between 0 and 1
p value 一定是接在0跟1之間的
So if the number of p value is larger
所以p value 的數字如果越大
It means that the degree of your support is not significant is higher
就代表你支持沒有顯著性的這種程度是越高的
So your result is not significant
所以你的結果就沒有顯著性
your result is not significant
你的結果就不具有顯著性
Conversely, if this value is smaller
反之如果這個值越小
means you support your data
就代表你支持你的數據
The results of your experiment support this conclusion significantly
你實驗的結果支持這個結論是有顯著
is insignificant the less the extent to which such hypotheses
是沒有顯著性的這樣的假說的程度越小
The smaller the degree of insignificance
那沒有顯著性的這個程度越小的話
that represents your result
那就代表你的結果
The degree of significance is higher
這個有顯著性的這個程度是越高的
So we generally do scientific research
所以我們一般做科學研究的人
is to hope that our p value
是希望我們的p value
is the smaller the better
是越小越好
Because this means that our experimental results are more significant
因為這代表我們的實驗結果是越有顯著性的
So this is also an example
所以這也是一個例子
That is to say, this modern statistical
就是說這個現代的統計學
is what we call an inferential statistic
是我們說是一個推論統計學
is a statistical inference
是一個統計推論
Because like P-Failure
因為像P-Failure
He just wants to learn from the samples you experimented with
他就是希望從你做實驗的樣本當中
to infer the results of real science
去推論到底真實的科學的結果
Is it of sufficient significance
是不是具有一個充分的顯著性
good
好
So basically we can say
所以基本上我們可以來說
this statistic
這個統計學
statistics is special
統計學很特別就是說
Although it is a
雖然它是一個
so to speak from mathematics
可以說是從數學
A discipline developed from applied mathematics
從應用數學發展出來的一個學問
But it is different from traditional mathematics
但是它跟傳統的數學
Traditional Applied Mathematics
傳統的應用數學
there is a very different place
有一個很不一樣的地方
just to say
就在於說
traditional mathematics
傳統的數學
more focus on the natural world
更多的是著重在自然界當中
a very definite rule
非常確定的一個規律
good
好
That
那
it's theirs
這是他們的
research object, such as Einstein's
的研究對象 譬如說 愛因斯坦提出的
1st class Mc squared or Newton's
1等Mc平方或是牛頓的
The constant rate of Newton's motion F and other MA these things
這個牛頓運動定率 F等MA這些東西
These are a very definite, very definite
這些都是一個非常確定 非常明確的
a law of nature
一個大自然運行的規律
That's what statisticians focus on
那但是統計學家他們著重的重點
is dealing with
卻是在處理
We are everywhere in our daily life
我們在日常生活當中 其實也無所不在的
This so-called uncertainty
這種所謂的不確定性 uncertainty
One of the founding fathers of this America
這個美國的這個開國元老之一
Franklin once said
富蘭克林曾經說過一段話
There are only two things that are certain in life
人生當中只有兩件事情是肯定的
everything else is uncertain
其他所有事情都是不確定的
Do you know what those two things are?
大家知道是哪兩件事情嗎
Death and taxes, right?
死亡跟交稅 對不對
It's May 1st and we have to pay taxes again, right?
馬上5月1號到了我們又要交稅了 對不對
So only death and paying taxes are two things
所以只有死亡跟交稅這兩件事情是
Everything else is uncertain
其他所有的事情都是 uncertain
Then we statisticians are actually
那我們統計學家其實就是
with these main
都要跟這些主要
The problems to be dealt with are these
要處理的問題都是這些
with uncertainty
跟 uncertainty 跟不確定性
related questions
有關的問題
The so-called statistical model
那所謂統計的模型
Its point is to go
它的重點就是要去
going to portray
要去刻畫
and to assess the magnitude of this uncertainty
並且去評估這種不確定性的大小
Then the so-called statistical inference
那麼所謂的統計推論
is to exist in uncertainty
就是要在不確定存在的
make statistical inferences in the current situation
現況當中去做統計推論
go from the tip of the iceberg
去從冰山的一角去
infer the truth
推測出真實的情況
So in the statistical chart
那所以在統計的圖表裡
we often see
我們常常看到的
not just one result
不是只有一個結果而已
Instead there will be a
而是會有一個
a degree of change up and down
上下的一個變化的程度
represents the uncertainty
代表的是這種不確定性
this error this possibility
這種誤差這種可能的
Another number term in our statistics is called
我們統計學的另外一個數語叫做
Mutations
變異
variation
variation
variation跟certity
variation跟certity
It is the same as arrow to some extent
跟arrow某種程度是一樣的
good
好
That
那
Statisticians are mainly
統計學家主要就是要
Statistics is mainly to
統計學主要就是要去
go
去
To make statistical inferences amidst these uncertainties
在這些不確定當中去做出統計推論
then making statistical inferences
那麼在做統計推論
What we pay more attention to is actually not the final result.
我們更重視的其實不是那個最後的結果而已
This result may be anyone can get one
這個結果也許誰都可以得到一個
some kind of result, right?
某種樣的結果對不對
But what?
可是呢
What about statistics?
統計學呢
It pays more attention to the process of getting this result
它更重視的是得到這個結果的過程
this process
這個過程
That is, we would like to say that the process is a
就是說我們會希望說這個過程是一個
best way
最佳的方法
The best
最佳的
A sort of
一種
ar
ar
program to get the result of this inference
程序來得到這個推論的結果
So the so-called
所以所謂的這個
This is what we call this statistical inference
這就是我們所謂的這個統計推論
This optimality in statistical inference
統計推論當中的這個最佳性
Optimality
Optimality
That's a matter of great importance in statistics.
那這個是統計學非常重視的事情
matter of great importance
非常重視的事情
So when we use statistics to make inferences,
所以我們統計學在做推論的時候
There must be a so-called objective function
一定會有一個所謂的目標函數
Our objective function
我們的目標函數
Usually a so-called likely-who direction
通常是一個所謂的likely-who方向
likely-who is a possibility
likely-who就是一種可能性
likelihood function
可能性函數
This likelihood refers to a statistical model
這個可能性指的是某個統計模型
which produces the data we observe
它會產生出我們所觀察到的數據
such a possibility
這樣的可能性
such a likely-who
這樣的likely-who
So this direction we call the likely-who direction
所以這樣的方向我們叫likely-who方向
so a good model
所以一個好的模型
It should make this like-if
它應該要使得這個like-if
how about the direction
方向怎麼樣
The bigger the better, right?
要越大越好對不對
Because it means that this model
因為就代表說這個模型
is more likely to produce
是越可能會產生
Is the data we see right now?
我們現在看到的數據的對不對
So that means
所以也就代表就是說
This model follows us
這個模型跟我們
The data actually seen is the best fit
實際上看到的數據是最吻合的
right? that's what it means
對不對 是這樣的意思
so our
所以我們的
we will have so-called
我們就會有所謂的
maximum likelihood
maximal likelihood
method of such inference
這樣的推論的方法
In fact, in some cases
這個方法其實在某些情況下
would also be equivalent to
也會等同於
more often heard
大家比較常聽到的
The so-called minimum frequency method
所謂的最小頻方法
minimum frequency method
最小頻方法
well then
好 那麼
In addition, our so-called
另外呢 我們這個所謂的
optimality
optimality
our best
我們的最佳性
also includes the so-called consistency
還包括了所謂的一致性
consistency
consistency
another way of saying it
那它的另外一種說
law of large numbers
叫做大數法則
You may hear this name more often.
大家可能比較常聽到的是這個名字
Law of large numbers
Law of large numbers
Then his statistical comparison
那他在統計上的比較
the professional term
這個專業的術語
called consistency
叫做一致性
consistency
consistency
what he meant was basically
他的意思基本上就是說
We want the outcome of our statistical inference
我們希望我們統計推論的結果
With the number of samples
隨著樣本數
when getting bigger
越來越大的時候
He was able to get closer and closer to the real result
他能夠越來越接近到真實的結果
this is called consistency
這個叫做一致性
consistency
consistency
on the other hand
那另外一方面
we also hope
我們也希望
In addition to this consistency
除了這個一致性之外
The results of our statistical inferences
我們統計推論的結果
effective
具有有效性
Efficiency
Efficiency
that means
這個意思就是說
we hope
我們希望
because of sampling
因為有抽樣
different sampling
不同的抽樣
have caused changes
有造成的變動
because just now
因為剛剛講
These data and data are all sampled.
這些資料這些數據都是抽樣來的
So different sampling will lead to different results
所以不同的抽樣會造成不同的結果
right
對不對
We expect such different outcome variations
我們希望這樣的不同的結果的變化
The smaller the impact on the outcome, the better
對於結果的影響是越小越好
The smaller the better
越小越好
This variation with sampling
這種隨著抽樣的變化而
What about the change in the result?
結果的變動呢
What about the smaller
越小的話呢
We say that its efficiency is higher
我們說它的efficiency是越高的
the more efficient it is the better
它的效率是越好的
What about statistical theory?
那麼在統計學的理論當中呢
In fact, it also gives
其實還給出了
In fact, we are in the general problem
其實我們在一般的問題當中
If we want to make statistical inferences
我們要做統計推論的話
In fact, we have a best standard
其實我們是有一個最好的標準的
That is the so-called information bound
也就是所謂的information bound的
This means our efficiency
這個就是說我們的efficiency
best possible
可以做到的最好的程度
highest efficiency
最高的efficiency
That is, the minimum degree of change
也就是變化最小的程度
With the change of sampling
隨著抽樣的變動而
minimum degree of change
變動的最小的程度
good so
好 所以
Such an Information Bound
那樣 這樣的一個Information Bound
just told us one like a
就告訴了我們的一個 就好像一個
test tell you
考試 告訴你
What is the full score of this test
這次考試的滿分是多少分
so you have a goal
所以你就有一個努力的目標
You can move towards that goal
你就可以朝那個目標呢 去前進
If you still can't reach that goal
那如果你還 達不到那個目標
You can also know that
你 你也可以知道就是說
How much room do you have to work hard
你還有多少的努力空間
Then this Efficiency
那 這個Efficiency
This Information Bound
這個Information Bound
involved a
牽涉到了一個
defined by our statistics
我們統計學所定義的
Information
就Information
Everyone is saying this word every day
大家天天在講這個字
Information Information message, right?
Information 資訊訊息 對不對
Then how do we define statistics
那我們統計學怎麼樣來定義
How much information is there in the so-called data
所謂數據裡面有多少的訊息量
Information basically
Information 基本上呢
we are based on
我們是根據
This Objective Function just mentioned
這個剛剛講的這個Objective Function
this objective function
這個目標函數
its this
它的這個
degree of bending
彎曲的程度
That is the so-called curvature Curvature
也就是所謂的曲率Curvature
to define
來定義的
Then let me ask you again
那我現在再請問大家一下
that is
就是說
Suppose our current goal
假設我們現在的目標
is the maximum required for this objective function
是要求這個目標函數的最大
This is the goal of our inference
這是我們的推論的目標
Then I want to ask everyone
那我想請問大家一下
that is
就是說
The red curve on the left
左邊這個紅色的曲線
with this blue curve on the right
跟右邊這個藍色的曲線
which curve do you think
你覺得哪一個曲線
Will give you more information
會給你更多的Information
Your goal is to ask for the maximum value
你的目標是要求那個幾大值
What do you think is the red curve
那你覺得是紅色的曲線
still blue curve
還是藍色的曲線
Will give you more information
會給你更多的Information
Why is it red on the left?
左邊紅色為什麼呢
the aunt
這位阿姨
right
對
can you tell me
可不可以講一下
perfectly accurate
完全正確
exactly that's it
exactly就是這樣的
Because of its large difference
因為它的差異比較大
so you can easily find
所以你很容易就可以找到
where is the best place
最好的那個位置在哪裡
right
對不對
that blue curve
那藍色的這條曲線
you will be more difficult
你就會比較困難了
because it feels the same
因為感覺都差不多
you can hardly find the best
你很難找到那個最好的
right
對不對
so what
所以呢
The information of our statistics
我們這個統計學的這個information
is through the curvature of our target content
就是透過我們的目標含數的曲率
Then we start from this elementary
那我們從這個初等為基分
we also know
我們也知道
In fact, the curvature of a curve
其實一個曲線的曲率
In fact, you can directly use this curve
其實就可以直接用這個曲線的
Secondary differentiation gives
二次微分就可以得到
right
對不對
So this is how we
所以我們就是透過這樣的方式
To measure the information in this data
來衡量這個數據當中的information
So this information
所以這個information
not just talk
不是只是嘴巴講講而已
In fact, our statistics have a clear way
其實我們統計學是有明確的一個方式
To measure this information
來度量這個information的
In addition we have the so-called
另外我們還有所謂的
near normality
近似常態性
It is also well-known in our statistics
也是我們統計學很有名的
central limit theorem
叫中央極限定理
This is mainly to describe
這個主要是在刻畫
Sampling
當剛剛講有抽樣
When sampling is changing
抽樣在變化的時候
How the results of our statistical inferences change
我們統計推論的結果怎麼變化
we want to say it will change
我們希望說它會有變化
But its change must have a law
但是它的變化要有一個規律
what's the rule
那有什麼規律呢
There will be such a law as the normal distribution
會有常態分布這樣的規律
so that we can have a
這樣我們就可以有一個
very convenient way to measure
很方便的方式去衡量
to calculate the uncertainty
去計算這個不確定性
Uncertainty due to sampling
因為抽樣所造成的不確定性
So here is an example
所以這邊就是舉個例子
Like this is the law of large numbers
像這個就是大數法則
Everyone may have seen this
這個大家可能都看過
That is to say, this S8 is the average of our sample
就是說這個S8就是我們樣本的平均數
The one below 41 445
下面那個41 445
4,6,7,18 This is its sample number
4,6,7,18 這個是它的樣本數
What about when you increase the number of samples
那你隨著樣本越來越增加的時候呢
You will find that this S8 slowly and slowly
你會發現這個S8慢慢慢慢的
close to a number
趨近到一個數字
In fact, it is close to 0.5, which is the one in our picture.
實際上是趨近到0.5 就是我們這個圖當中的這個
red line
紅色的這條線
Then this 0.5 is indeed
那這個0.5也的確就是
average for this group
這個群體的平均值
So this picture is to tell you
所以這個圖呢是告訴大家
a thing called the law of large numbers
一個所謂大數法則這樣的事情
We just talked about this statistical inference
我們剛剛講就是說這個統計推論
What about this statistic?
這個統計量呢
will gradually increase with the number of samples
會隨著這個樣本數的增加逐漸的
close to the mean of our true population
接近到我們真正群體的平均數值
Like that poll, right?
就好像那個民意調查一樣對不對
When you poll if you interview more and more people
當你民意調查如果你訪問越來越多人的話
Why
哎
The result of this visit is getting closer to
這個訪問的結果呢就為越來越接近於
The support of the people in this truly all northern and northern accumulation areas
這個真正全部北北積地區的民眾的支持度
how many
有多少
so
所以
This is called the law of large numbers
這個是所謂的大數法則
What about the other thing? This is the central limit theorem just mentioned.
那另外呢 這是剛剛講的這個中央極限定理
normality of eating
也就是進食常態性
This is just the average
這個就是把剛剛的這個平均數呢
it's always changing, right?
它會一直在變動對不對
But we record all the process of its changes
但是我們把它變動的所有的過程記錄下來
and then put all occurrences of
然後把它所有出現過的
only into one
只化成一個
The so-called fat map, the fat map we learned as children
所謂的脂肪圖 我們小時候學的脂肪圖
right
對不對
Just look at its distribution
就是看它的分布狀況
Distribution from large to small
由大到小的分布狀況
that's what i just said
那就是我剛剛講的
that is
就是說
Although it will keep moving
雖然它會一直在動來動去
right
對不對
but you will find
可是你會發現呢
this
這個
Well
呃
What is the law of its change?
它的這個變化的規律呢
actually it
其實它
Although big and small, right?
雖然有大有小對不對
but you can find
可是你可以發現
When you fatten all of it from big to small into one
當你把它所有由大到小的脂化成一個
When the fat map is presented
脂肪圖呈現出來的時候
It is very close to a normal distribution
它是非常接近一個常態分布的
What is a normal distribution
什麼是常態分布
It's the blue line behind
就是背後這條藍色的線
blue line
藍色的線
Then the width of this normal distribution
那這個常態分布的寬度
reflect the extent to which we have changed
就反映了我們變化的程度
right
對不對
What about the width?
那這個寬度呢
Basically what Vice President Zhou just said
基本上就是剛剛周副院長講的
One part of the root of n
根號n分之一
such a width
這樣的寬度
So the width is just in the process of changing
所以這個寬度剛剛在變動的過程當中
everyone can see
大家可以看到
Because the square root sign is n/1
因為根號n分之一嘛
So when n gets bigger and bigger
所以n越來越大的時候
Its width is getting smaller and smaller
它的寬度是越來越小的
So the extent of our change is getting smaller and smaller
所以代表我們變化的程度是越來越小的
getting smaller
越來越小的
So we get more and more accurate results
所以我們會得到越來越精確的結果
And this level of precision
而這個精確的程度
It is possible to use a very simple normal distribution
是可以用一個很簡單的常態分布
to characterize it to measure it
去刻畫它去度量它的
good
好
Then here I am simple
那在這邊呢我簡單的
When Zhou Fuyuechang was mentioned in the introduction at the beginning, it means
當這個周復月長一開始在介紹的時候提到就是說
In fact, statistics is a
其實統計學是一個
A knowledge that can be applied in a variety of different fields
可以應用在各種不同的領域的一個學問
In fact, it is also an instrumental science
實際上它也是一門工具性的學問
Just like a computer, like information
就好像電腦一樣 資訊一樣
it is used as a tool
它是作為一種工具
can be used for a variety of problems
是可以用在各種不同的問題上面的
good
好
So actually I thought about it myself and said
所以實際上我自己想了一下就是說
Statistics for the entire scientific community
統計學到底對於這整個科學界
What major contributions have you made?
做了哪些重大的貢獻呢
Then I list these three
那以下我列舉了這三項
But what I want to tell you is to say
但是要跟大家講的就是說
This is only limited to my personal
這只是局限於我個人的
because of my own field of study
因為我自己的研究領域
So I know these three
所以我比較知道是這三個
Of course other statisticians
那當然其他的統計學家
may have different answers
可能會有不同的答案
But I don't think these three are the only three
但是我覺得這三個不是唯一的三個
what i just said
我剛剛講的
But they do, I think, very important contributions
但是他們的確我覺得是非常重要的貢獻
The first is the so-called case control study
第一個是所謂的case control study
case control study
病例對照研究
The second is the so-called EM algorithm
第二個是所謂的EM演算法
The third is the so-called Kephenmeyer curve
第三個是所謂的Kephenmeyer curve
So let me introduce to you
那麼底下我來跟大家介紹一下
The first I think is a very big contribution
第一個我認為非常大的貢獻
It is a case control study
是case control study
case control study is called case control study in Chinese
case control study是中文叫做病例對照研究
This is now widely used in public health
這個是現在廣泛應用在公共衛生
in medicine in public health
在醫學 在公共衛生
A research method in the field of epidemiology
在流行病學領域的一種研究方法
This method does something like this
這個方法的做法就是這樣
That is to say, suppose you want to study Western Tobacco
就是說假設你要研究西菸
Will it be easy to get scrapped
會不會容易得到廢
The traditional approach may be that you have to watch a group of
那傳統上的做法可能就是說你要看一群
Following a group of CN people
追蹤一群CN的人
Then look at the proportion of them getting lung cancer 5 years later and 10 years later
然後看他們5年後10年後得到肺癌的比例
right
對不對
Then watch a bunch of this
然後再看一群這個
People who are not CN, right?
不CN的人對不對
Same tracking for 5 years and 10 years
一樣追蹤5年10年
Then look at his rate of getting lung cancer
然後看他這個得到肺癌的比例
Then do a comparison, right?
然後做一個比較對不對
This way you can draw a conclusion saying
這樣你就可以得出一個結論說
Is there any relationship between CN and lung cancer?
CN跟肺癌會不會有關係
What about proportional control studies?
那麼比例對照研究呢
he did this
他是這樣做的
he didn't do that
他並不是這樣做
because doing so
因為這樣做的話
you spend a lot of time
你要花很多的時間
you're going to track down
你要去追蹤
That's what the proportional control study did
那比例對照研究是這樣做的
That is to say, he went directly to the hospital
就是說他直接到醫院裡面
Just go to the oncology department, for example, right?
就去找譬如說腫瘤科對不對
He went to find a patient with lung cancer, right?
他就去找肺癌的病人對不對
Then, for example, he goes to the Chiayi Division again, right?
然後譬如說他再到嘉義科對不對
Family medicine, he went to the guy who didn't have lung cancer.
家庭醫學科他去找那個沒有肺癌的人
patients without lung cancer
沒有肺癌的病人
But he's probably just here to add one for a health check
可是他可能只是來加一顆做個健康檢查
Or watch a diarrhea or catch a cold
或者是看個拉肚子 看個感冒
so he doesn't have lung cancer
所以他沒有肺癌
So you go directly to these two groups of people
所以你直接找這兩群人
and ask them if they smoke
然後去問他們有沒有吸煙
Then you directly compare
然後你直接去比較
So such a
所以這樣的一種
The research method is called
研究的方法叫做
case-control study
病例對照研究法
Then this method is from
那這個方法是從
Early 20th century around 1910s and 1920s
20世紀初大概1910、1920年代
Began to appear in medical professional journals
開始出現在醫學的專業期刊
Such studies are beginning to be reported
開始有這樣的研究被報導出來
The main research object at that time was
當時主要的研究對象是
The relationship between smoking and lung cancer
抽煙跟肺癌的關係
And this birth history
還有這個生育史
women's reproductive history
婦女的生育史
has he ever had a child
他有沒有生過小孩
how many children were born
生過幾個小孩
At what age did he have his first child
他第一次生小孩的年齡是幾歲
in connection with his subsequent breast cancer
跟他後來得到乳癌的關係
So at the beginning of the 20th century, this kind of
所以在20世紀初開始慢慢有這種
Case Control study of this kind of research is reported
Case Control study的這種研究被報導出來
At that time, at that time, it caused a great deal of
那當時呢 當時呢 引起了非常
caused a lot of controversy in the scientific community
在科學界引起了非常非常多的爭論
why
為什麼呢
Because it should be easy for everyone to see
因為大家應該可以很容易看出來
That is to say, traditionally we statistically analyze
就是說傳統上我們統計分析
so-called representative sample
都是要所謂的代表性的樣本
right? for example
對不對 譬如說
We often say that you are clearly inaccurate in the investigation
我們常常講 你明明調查不準
Because your sample is not representative
因為你的樣本沒有代表性
right
對不對
So what about our statistical analysis?
所以我們統計分析呢
What is often required is
常常要求的是
Our premise is to have a
我們前提是要有一個
representative的sample
representative的sample
a representative sample
一個具有代表性的樣本
The sample obtained from the Case Control study
那Case Control study所得到的樣本
Obviously not a representative sample
明顯的不是代表性樣本
right
對不對
For example, if I take 100 today
譬如說我如果今天取100
100 lung cancer patients
100個肺癌的病患
With 100 patients without lung cancer
跟100個沒有肺癌的病患
What about this?
那這樣子呢
inside my sample
在我的樣本裡面
The rate of lung cancer is 50%
肺癌的比率是50%
right
對不對
But in all Taiwan
可是在全台灣
of all groups
全部的群體當中
rate of lung cancer
肺癌的比率
is far less than this 50%
是遠小於這個50%的
right
對不對
So this sample
所以這個樣本
obviously not a
明顯的不是一個
representative sample
representative sample
So how can he be used to infer
所以他怎麼可以用來推論
What is the relationship between smoking and lung cancer?
抽菸跟肺癌的關係呢
or
或者是
Women's reproductive history with him
婦女生育史跟他
What about breast cancer?
乳癌的關係呢
so this time
所以這當時
caused a very, very big debate
引起了非常非常大的爭論
So until this about the 1950s
所以一直到這個大概1950年代
This is it
就是這個
The statistician Jeromey Kohnfield
這位統計學家Jeromey Kohnfield
he is this american
他是這個美國
National Cancer Institute
國家癌症研究所
a statistician of
的一位統計學家
He is theoretically
他就是從理論上面
from mathematics to statistics
從數學從統計的
In theory to confirm this case control study
在理論上面去證實了這個case control study
The results of his analysis
他得到的分析結果
his effectiveness
他的有效性
his correctness
他的這個正確性
With you just now you followed the smoker directly
跟你剛剛你直接追蹤抽菸的人
track non-smokers
追蹤不抽菸的人
Then look at the results of his last illness
然後看他最後發病的結果
This correctness is exactly the same as
這種正確性是完全一樣的
He clarified the fact that
他釐清了這樣的一個事實
then after him
然後在他之後
There are more and more statisticians
就有越來越多的統計學家
to further develop
去進一步的發展
to refine this sort of case-control study
去改良這種各種各樣的病例對照研究
So some research methods like this
所以這樣的一些研究方法
also facilitated this
也就促進了這個
Many studies on this etiology
很多對於這個病因的研究
research on disease prevention
還有對於疾病防治的研究
in medicine
在醫學方面
so like this guy
所以像這個人
This man is actually an epidemic
這個人其實是一個流行病
Pathologist, he said in his book
病學家 那他在他的書裡面就說了
say it
說了就是說
List of sophisticated use and understanding of case control
List of sophisticated use and understanding of case control
studies is the most outstanding
studies is the most outstanding
mestarch development of modern
mestarch development of modern
epidemiology
epidiology
So he said it himself
所以他自己都說了 在
modern epidemiology
現代的流行病學 epidiology
The word is epidemiology
這個字就是流行病學
Epidemiology in modern times
在流行 近代的流行病學
One of the most outstanding achievements is the
最傑出的一項成就就是
The use and understanding of case-control research methods
病例對照研究方法的使用跟瞭解
behind this
那這個背後
In fact, the biggest contribution is the contribution of statisticians
其實最大的貢獻是統計學家的貢獻
Because it's up to the statisticians to figure it out.
因為是統計學家去釐清了
this
這個
case control study his validity his correctness
case control study 他的有效性 他的正確性
and further refine his method
然後並進一步完善他的方法
Okay, the second important contribution I want to make is
好 那第二個我要舉的這個很重要的貢獻
Statistically important contributions to the scientific community
統計學很重要的貢獻 對於科學界
is the so-called
是所謂的
hospital algorithm
的醫院演算法
So
那麼
The hospital algorithm has actually been
醫院演算法其實已經被
used in many, many different fields
用在非常非常多不同的領域了
like
像是
Like this Machine Learning
像是這個Machine Learning
very red now
現在很紅的
active learning
積極學習
or like medical imaging
或者是像醫學影像
or something like this
或者是像這個
Psychological Dosimetry
心理 劑量學
volume psychology
積量心理學
fake finance
偽像財務
Financial Engineering
財務工程學
this kind of
這一類的
different fields
不同的領域
will use this algorithm
都會用這種演算法
to calculate
來計算
the result they want
他們要的結果
What about this method?
那這個方法呢
In fact, it was first created by three
其實是最早是由三位
The Harvard Statistics Department
這個哈佛大學統計系的
proposed by the professor
教授所提出來的
about 40 years ago
在大概40年前
proposed an algorithm
提出來的一個演算法
What about this algorithm?
那這個演算法呢
that is
就是說
It basically takes our Model
它基本上就是把我們的Model
divided into observed parts
分成了觀察到了部分
with the unobserved part
跟沒有觀察到的部分
hidden part
隱藏起來的部分
and parameters
以及參數
Then what about the so-called unobserved
然後呢 沒有觀察的所謂的
1 here is a 1
1 這邊有一個1
1 what about this thing
1呢 這個東西呢
means to mean
就是代表就是說
You just put the part that you didn't observe
你就是把沒有觀察到的這個部分呢
you take his average
你就取他的一個平均值
take one of his expectations
取他的一個期望值
because he can't see
因為他看不到嘛
So you use his expectations to
所以你就用他的期望值來
bring it in
把它帶進去
fill it in
把它填補進去
What about the expected value?
那這個期望值呢 是
of course it is
當然這是
conditional expected value
一種我們叫條件期望值
It is given in the part we have seen
它是給定在我們已經看到的部分
and the current parameter value
還有目前的參數值
calculated by a
所計算出來的一個
expected expectations
預期的期望值
OK, after I bring you in
好 將你帶進去以後
you can like this
你就可以 好像這個
You see everything you see, right?
每看到的東西就看到了 對不對
So you can directly address the goal just mentioned
所以你就可以直接對剛剛講的這個目標
Contain numbers to maximize
含數去進行最大 最大化
Do you want to optimize
對不對 進行最佳化
to get a parameter value
去得到一個參數值
After getting the new parameter value
那得到了新的參數值以後
You go to update the original expectation
你再去更新這個原來的這個期望值
Because this expected value will be related to the parameter value
因為這個期望值會跟參數值有關
Go to update and then do the maximum
再去更新 然後再做最大
So this algorithm is an iterative process
所以這個演算法是一個迭代的過程
it ends up with this
它最後會這個
converge to a final result
收斂到一個最後的結果
So one is called E step and the other is called M step
所以一個叫E step 一個叫M step
E is to calculate an average, to calculate an expected value
E就是算一個平均 算一個期望值
M is to seek the optimization of the target content
M就是求這個目標含數的最佳化
So the combination of E and M is the EM algorithm
所以E跟M合起來就是EM演算法
So what is the benefit of this algorithm?
那這個演算法就是說它的好處是什麼
The first one is very general
第一個 它非常general
It can be used for a variety of different problems
它可以用到各種不同的問題
that is
就是說
You don't need for a different problem
你不需要為了一個不一樣的問題
to design a different algorithm
去設計一個不一樣的演算法
In fact, later found
其實後來發現
Many, many different algorithms that people are already using
很多很多大家已經在使用的不同的演算法
can be put into the framework of this EM algorithm.
都可以放到這個EM演算法的架構下來進行
So you just need to master this basic principle
所以就是說你只要掌握到這個基本的原則
It is the two steps of E and M
就是E跟M這兩個步驟
you will
你會了
You can calculate many, many problems
你就可以計算這很多很多的問題
So this is a very big contribution
所以這是非常大的貢獻
Another great contribution is that
另外一個很大的貢獻就是說
This EM algorithm is a very stable algorithm
這個EM演算法是一個非常穩定的演算法
That is to say, every time it is carried out
就是說它每一次的進行
will catch your target
都會讓你的目標含住
in further optimization
在進一步的優化
further bigger
進一步的更大
or better
或者是更好
so
所以
It means you're always going in the right direction
就是說你永遠是往對的方向走
you won't go wrong
你不會走冤枉路
you are always going
你永遠是往
one of the best places to go
一個最好的地方在走的
So this is the EM algorithm
所以這個是EM演算法
The third example I'm going to talk about is this
那第三個我要講的例子是這個
The so-called Kippelmeyer Curve
所謂的Kippelmeyer Curve
This is two peoples
這個是兩個人民
two peoples
兩個人民
two peoples two statisticians
兩個人民 兩個統計學家
What does this curve do?
那這個curve是做什麼呢
it is going to be estimated
它是要來估計
This kind of curve actually I think
這個這樣的curve其實我想
doing if there is this
在做如果有這個
is a biomedical background
是生物醫學背景的這種
especially the words of the researchers
特別是研究人員的話
may be very familiar
可能會非常熟悉
especially doctors
特別是醫生
you may very well be in
你可能非常會在
See such graphics on medical journals
醫學的期刊上面看到這樣的圖形
what is this
這個是什麼
this is one
這個就是一個
This is a group of patients
就是一群病人的這個
you have to estimate it
你要去估算它的
survival curve
存活曲線
survival rate
存活率
So what about the Y axis?
所以這個Y軸呢
represents the survival rate
代表的就是存活率
Survival rate, so you can see it's 1 at the beginning, right?
存活率 所以你可以看到 一開始是1 對不對
In the beginning, everyone survived
一開始大家都都是 這個存活的
Then gradually as time goes on
然後逐漸的 隨著很久是時間
Over time it will, the survival rate will
隨著時間呢 它會 存活率會
when you have someone gradually passing away
當你有人逐漸的過世的話
Your survival rate will keep dropping
你的存活率就會一直的往下掉
So what is this district line like?
所以 這個區線是什麼樣的區線
It is to tell you that this group of patients their
它就是告訴你這群病人他們的
A situation in which survival rates decrease over time
存活率 隨著時間 遞減的一個情況
So doctors often have such zone lines
所以醫生常常有這樣的區線
Let's see, for example, the five-year survival rate for cancer
來看看 譬如說癌症的五年存活率
data like this is very important to them
這樣的數據 這對他們是很重要的
A tool that this survival zone line
一個工具 那這種存活區線
In fact, it is not simple at all
其實背後是一點都不簡單的
so we have to
所以我們要
But the so-called survival rate means
但所謂的存活率就是說
For example, he just said this picture
他在譬如說他剛剛這個圖
What are the chances that he just lived past 10 months?
他剛剛要活過10個月的機率有多少
then you go and see
那你就去看看
His chances of this his time over 10 months
他這個他的時間超過10個月的機率
You even count, right?
你就算一算對不對
But the reality is not so simple
可是現實的情況沒有這麼簡單
because
是因為呢
if you think about it
如果你想想看
if you today
如果你今天
what you want to see today is
你今天要看的是
50 month survival rate
50個月的存活率的話
that may be a lot of people
那可能很多人呢
that is
就是說
That is to say, 50 months is about a few years
就是說50個月大概是幾年
4 years right?
4年對不對
4 years
4年
and you
那你
You are going to record this result today
你今天是要記錄這個結果的
Maybe you're doing a clinical study
可能你要做一個臨床研究
right
對不對
But what?
可是呢
Although you said you want
你雖然說你要
you want to get a 50
你想要得到一個50
50 months is a survival rate of over 4 years, right?
50個月就是4年多的一個存活率 對不對
But maybe you can't wait that long
可是可能你沒有辦法等那麼久
you can't wait that long
你沒有辦法等那麼久
That means you may have to within 3 years
也就是說你可能必須在3年內
You will have a statistical result
你就要有一個統計的結果
so it becomes
所以就變成說
some people if he
有一些人如果他
when he was 3 years old
他在3年的時候
he is alive
他還存活的
You can't see the real age of death of these people
這些人你就看不到他真正的死亡的年齡
because you can't
因為你沒有辦法
Because some people he will survive longer
因為有一些人他會存活的比較久
But your observation time is limited
可是你的觀察時間是有限的
is limited
是有限的
you can't help
你沒有辦法
Everyone tracked down his real death
每一個人都追蹤到他真正的死亡
So this would result in
所以這樣就會造成
Some complexity of our data
我們數據的一些複雜度
you're at the end of three years
你到三年就要結束了
so all you know is to say
所以你只能知道就是說
he lived for three years
他活了三年
but you have no way of knowing
但是你沒有辦法知道
how long did he really survive
他真正存活了多久
because after three years
因為三年之後
You no longer observe this patient
你就沒有再觀察這個病人了
Follow up with this patient again
再追蹤這個病人了
What about the other side?
那另外一方面呢
There are some other possibilities
還有一些可能就是說
Maybe it's not a matter of you not having enough time to observe
也許不是因為你觀察時間不夠的問題
Maybe even this patient
甚至可能是這個病人呢
He may have been transferred midway.
他也許就中途轉院了
or he moved
或是他搬家了
you will never find him
你就根本找不到他了
So maybe at twenty months he
所以也許他在二十個月的時候
he is alive and well
他還活得好好的
But he moved next
可是他接下來他搬家了
you won't be able to contact him
你就聯絡不到他了
So what about this kind of person?
所以這種人呢
also cause
也會造成
This complexity in our data
我們數據上的這種複雜
We are going to do this kind of data
我們就要做這種數據呢
We call it Sensor Data
我們就叫Sensor Data
Sensor Data
Sensor Data
So how about this kind of Sensor Data
所以怎麼樣在這種Sensor Data
in the presence of
存在的情況下
to get a correct
去得到一個正確的
survival curve survival curve
存活曲線 存活率曲線的
What about this estimate?
這個估計呢
Inference?
推論呢
this is a
這個是一個
It's actually not a simple question
其實是一個不太簡單的問題
That is also through Kepham and Meyer
那也是經由了Kepham跟Meyer
Where are the two statisticians?
這兩位統計學家呢
They discovered the method
他們發現了這種方法
So we'll call it now
所以我們現在就把它叫做
Kepham-Meyer Curve
Kepham-Meyer Curve
Or called Proud-Limit Curve
或者叫Proud-Limit Curve
So what about the doctor now?
所以現在的醫生呢
Although he may only be able to observe
儘管他可能只能觀察
one short year short three years
短短的一年 短短的三年
Or that although his patients may
或者是說儘管他的病人可能
some will be lost in the middle
有一些中途會流失掉
will not see these patients
會看不到這些病人
won't find these patients
會找不到這些病人
but it doesn't matter
但是沒有關係
he can still
他還是可以
According to the collected
根據他所收集到的這些
whether complete data
不管是完整的數據
Or these so-called Sensor Data
還是這些所謂的Sensor Data
he can
他都可以
to get one of these patients
去得到一個這些病人的
This curve of survival
存活率的這個曲線
So this is the Gibbon-Mine Curve
所以這個是Gibbon-Mine Curve
good
好
Okay, so is there any problem with the above?
好 所以以上有沒有什麼問題
So my background has taken an hour
所以我的背景已經花了一個鐘頭了
So I only have 30 minutes left for my example
所以我只剩下30分鐘來講我的例子
good
好
Well, that's our topic today
好 那這也是我們今天的主題
that is
就是
What the statistics are doing I used two examples
統計學在做什麼 我用了兩個例子
What I must tell you is that
那必須要跟大家說明的是
Of course statistics are doing too much
當然統計學在做的事情實在太多了
The examples I can give are very limited to my own
那我能夠舉的例子只是非常局限在我個人
very limited experience
非常有限的經驗
So I'm sure you can learn from other statisticians
所以我相信你可以從其他的統計學家
get more interesting examples
得到更多更有趣的例子
That
那
My first example is earthquake risk assessment
我的第一個例子是地震風險評估
This is actually me
這個其實是我跟
i used to
我之前跟
When I first became an actor, I told the world
我剛進中演員的時候就跟這個地球所的
A researcher Cai Sovereign, Teacher Cai
一位研究員蔡主權 蔡老師
A study we collaborated on
我們合作的一個研究
That is to continue with this
那目前是繼續跟這個
Dr. Zhao from the National Earthquake Engineering Research Center
國家地震工程研究中心的趙博士
Zhao Chuxian Dr. Zhao
趙出顯 趙博士
We continue our research on this
我們繼續這方面的研究
Then I think everyone knows about earthquakes
那我想地震大家都知道
This one is of course for us
這個是當然是對我們是一個
big threat in taiwan
很大的威脅 在台灣
Then this is the earthquakes that happened in the past few years
那這個就是我們過去這幾年發生的這些地震的這些
The location of the repression and the larger the circles represent
鎮壓的位置 然後這些圈圈如果越大的話代表
The scale of its earthquake is bigger
它的地震的這個叫規模是越大的
well then
好 那麼
Earthquake Engineers One Thing They're Important
地震工程學家他們很重要的一件事情
is to construct these earthquake-measured
是要去建構根據地震所測到的這些
The so-called surface acceleration is when the earthquake shakes
所謂地表加速度 就是地震在搖的時候
They will have an instrument measuring the acceleration of our surface
他們會有一個儀器在測量這個我們地表的加速度
It is very important for earthquake engineers to establish this
那地震工程學家很重要的一件事情是要去建立這個
this surface acceleration
這個地表加速度
This is the skewed axis of the graph. Surface acceleration.
這是這個圖的歪軸 地表加速度
With the crackdown distance away from me this car
隨著鎮壓的距離 離我這個車
The distance from my measuring station to my location
離我這個測站 離我這個地點的距離
one of
的一個
Attenuation situation
衰減的情形
We know that if the distance
我們知道如果距離
If the suppression is farther away, of course the surface acceleration will be smaller
這個鎮壓如果越遠 當然這個地表加速度就會越小
Because the repression will be less
因為鎮壓會比較小
Right, the closer you are, the greater the suppression
對不對 如果越近 鎮壓比較大
So the surface acceleration will be greater
所以地表加速度就會越大
there is another one
那另外還有一個
The factor that affects this surface acceleration is of course the size of the earthquake.
因素會影響這個地表加速度的當然就是地震的規模
The scale is extremely extreme earthquake
規模 是極極極的地震
so
所以
It is important for earthquake engineers to construct this so-called
地震工程學家很重要的一件事是要建構這個所謂
Attenuation Model of Surface Acceleration
地表加速度的衰減模型
According to this model, he can go
根據這個模型呢 他可以去
predict
預測
These data are from these points are this
這些資料都是從這些點都是這個
These so-called seismic strong and low motion stations
所謂的地震 強低動測站的這些
The actual data measured by surface acceleration
地表加速度測到的實際的數據
That
那
One of their very important things is to construct from these data
他們很重要的一件事情是要從這些數據裡面去建構
to predict a place
去預測某個地點
For example, a nuclear power plant
譬如說一個核電廠
or a school
或是一個學校
or a subway station
或是一個捷運站
That location is at a certain suppression distance
那個地點在某個鎮壓距離
and below the scale of an earthquake
以及在某個地震的規模之下
how much ground acceleration will it have
它會有多大的地表加速度
Build engineering staff from here
從這邊就可以建設工程人員
to build a nuclear power plant
要建核電廠
Or to build a subway station
或是要建捷運站
Or the engineers who want to build the school
或是要建學校的工程人員
to design their building
就可以去設計他們這個建築物
How strong is the seismic coefficient
要有多強的抗震係數
or safety factor
或者是安全係數
So this is a very important job for them
所以這個是他們很重要的一個工作
this is what they call
這個是他們叫做
Ground motion attenuation model or surface acceleration attenuation model
地動衰減模型或者是地表加速度衰減模型
What about this curve?
那這條曲線呢
is their mathematical model
就是他們的數學模型
The mathematical model they constructed
他們所建構的數學模型
but what about the blue dot
但是藍色的點呢
is the actual measured data
是實際的測量的數據
So from here you can see that
所以從這邊大家可以看到就是說
What about the data?
這些數據呢
Compared to this model
相對於這個模型來講
still showed a very large
還是顯現出了非常大的
Uncertainty right?
不確定性對不對
That is to say, if you want to use this
就是說你如果要用這條
this model
這個模型
This is actually a so-called statistical regression model
這事實上是一個所謂的統計上的回歸模型
From such a regression model to predict
從這樣的一個回歸模型來預測
an actual earthquake
一個實際發生的地震
the ground acceleration it causes
它造成的地表加速度
there is still a lot of uncertainty
還是有很大的不確定性
There is still a big error, right?
還是有很大的誤差對不對
great degree of change
很大的變化的程度
So at first
所以當初呢
As I just said, we have a lot of these book exhibitions in Taiwan
就剛剛講的 我們在臺灣有很多的這些冊展
Most of these book exhibitions are set up in primary and secondary schools.
這些冊展大部分建在中小學裡面
When an earthquake occurs there are measurements of surface acceleration
當地震發生的時候就會有地表加速度的測量值
These are the blue dots we just had
這個就是我們剛剛的這些藍色的點
So the question we now have to ask is
所以我們現在要問的問題就是說
is there any way we can say
我們有沒有辦法就是說
in just this
在剛剛的這個
a model, right?
一個模型 對不對
Then there's an error in the actual ground acceleration, right?
然後實際的地表加速度當中有一個誤差 對不對
Is there any way for us to further reduce this error?
那我們有沒有辦法進一步的把這個誤差縮小
how to shrink it
怎麼去縮小呢
That is to say, is there any way for us to convert this error
就是說我們有沒有辦法把這個誤差
take this uncertainty
把這個不確定性
uncertainty
uncertainty
further broken down into
進一步的分解成
this
這個
this is just now
這個是剛剛
The mathematical model of this is to consider the scale of the earthquake
的數學模型 這個就是考慮了地震的規模
After the distance from Zhenyang
跟震陽的距離以後的
model, but the latter is full of errors
模型 但是後面都是誤差
That
那
The decomposition of this error we would hope for
這個誤差我們會希望的分解
It is hoped that further decomposition into
希望進一步的分解成
One is the error caused by different earthquakes
一個是因為不同的地震所產生的誤差
So that is to say, this part of the error can be determined by
所以也就是說 這部分的誤差是可以由
explained by the characteristics of the earthquake itself
地震本身的特性來解釋的
What about the other component of the error?
那另外這個誤差的成分呢 是
Because of the nature of the station and the location itself
因為這個測站 這個地點本身的特性
caused by
所造成的
So this error is different locations
所以這個誤差是不同的地點
Because some of it may be a basin
因為它有的可能是盆地
Some may be on this hard rock
有的可能是在這個堅硬的岩石上
some may be in the sand
有的可能是在沙地上
So it will cause its surface acceleration to be different
所以會造成它的地表加速都不一樣
So this part of the error?
所以這部分的誤差呢
Because of
是因為
This part of this uncertainty
這部分的這個不確定性
is due to the characteristics between different locations
是因為不同的地點之間的特性所造成的
this change
這種變化
this fairwayation
這種fairwayation
what about the end
那最後呢
The rest of this is that we can't have the properties of the earthquake itself
這個剩下的部分就是我們沒有辦法有地震本身的特性
or this error explained by the geological properties of the site itself
或者是地點本身的地質特性所解釋的這個誤差
so what
所以呢
all we have to do is say
我們要做的事情就是說
Mr. Cai
當初蔡老師
when we come to discuss this issue
我們來討論這個問題的時候呢
we just wanted to say
我們就是在想說
Is there a way outside of the original regression model
有沒有辦法在原來的回歸模型之外
take this further
進一步的把這個
regression model
回歸模型的
The remaining error
剩下的這個誤差
remaining uncertainty
剩下的不確定性
take this further
進一步的把這個
Uncertainty caused by the earthquake itself
地震本身所造成的不確定性
take it
把它
jump out
跳出來
and because the location itself
然後因為地點本身
Uncertainty caused by the properties of Single it out
的特性造成的不確定性 把它挑出來
In this case, when we make predictions later,
這樣的話 之後我們要做預測的時候
According to the characteristics of the earthquake itself,
就可以根據地震本身的特性
and the characteristics of the place itself
以及地點本身的特性
Further send this error to it
進一步地把這個誤差給它派出掉
So a more accurate error can be obtained
所以就可以得到更精確的誤差
more accurate predictions
更精確的預測
So here's our question
所以這就是我們的問題
our problem our approach
我們的問題 我們的方法
In fact, using our statistics
其實又是用我們統計上
A very common tool in statistics
統計學非常普遍的一個工具
is a so-called mixed effects model
就是一個所謂的混合效應模型
or a random effects model
或者是隨機效應模型
We add the original regression model to
我們把原來的回歸模型再加上
Due to the random effect caused by the earthquake
因為地震所造成的隨機效應
and because of different locations
以及因為不同的地點
Random effects caused by different strategies
不同的策戰所造成的隨機效應
We all assume that this water accumulation effect is a normal distribution
這個水積效應 我們都假設它是一個常態的分布
is the normal distribution of the central limit theorem we just saw
就是我們剛剛看到的那個中央極限定理的常態分布
So what we want to know now is this normal distribution
所以我們現在 我們想要知道的就是這個常態分布
Just mentioned its width, how much does it change
剛剛講的它的寬度 它的變化有多少
Because of this change, such as the effect of an earthquake
因為這個變化 比如說地震的效應
The variation and width of its normal distribution can tell me
它的這個常態分布的這個變異 這個寬度就可以告訴我
That is, because of the earthquake, this can be explained
就是說因為地震所這個可以解釋的這種
How much is this variation of farration How much is this ingredient
farration這種變化有多少 這種成分有多少
Then this location its normal distribution its this
然後這個地點 它的常態分布 它的這個
mutate it to this width
變異 它的這個寬度
it tells me that because of the location
它就告訴我因為地點
What is the extent of the change
所造成的變化程度有多少
and finally this
然後最後是這個
not explained by any reason that we know of
沒有辦法由我們所知道的任何原因所解釋的
this kind
這種
How much does the error vary
誤差它的變化程度有多少
so
所以
This is the parameter we want to know
這個就是我們想要了解的參數
Known parameters
了解的參數
So we just pass
所以我們就是透過
EM just said
剛剛講的EM
algorithm
演算法
to perform this calculation on this model
來對這個模型進行這個計算
Calculation
進行計算
So we also have the so-called E-STEP
所以我們一樣有所謂的E-STEP
Follow M-STEP
跟M-STEP
E-STEP is to calculate
E-STEP就是去計算
the parts of us that don't see
我們那些沒有看到的部分的
those papers
那些紙
what's the missing part
那沒有看到的部分是什麼呢
That's what I just said
就是剛剛講的這些
earthquake
地震
the effect of
所造成的效應或者是
Place
地點
The effect
造成的效應
Why can't I see it? It's because
這為什麼沒有辦法看到呢 是因為
he has been with
他已經跟
Just now, these things in front of this are all mixed together.
剛剛的這個前面的這些東西都混在一起了
And the last error all mixed up
還有最後的誤差都混在一起了
We only saw this Y at the end
我們最後只看到這個Y
Y is our surface acceleration
Y就是我們的地表加速度
So we have no way of actually seeing
所以我們沒有辦法實際的看到
Effects due to seismic properties
地震特性造成的影響
Effects on Surface Acceleration
對地表加速度造成的影響
and the characteristics of the place
還有地點的特性
So these are the parts that we don't see
所以這些都是我們沒有看到的部分
So we use Y
所以我們用Y
replace it then max
把它取代然後最大
then this
然後這個
always
一直的
overlapping tape finally converges it
疊帶最後把它收斂
so
所以
I skipped all of these
這些我都跳過去了
these are mathematical formulas
這些都是數學式子
i just skip it
我就把它跳過去
so in the end
所以最後呢
We can get these parameters
我們就可以得到這些參數
components of these errors
這些誤差的成分
These parameters of the composition of these changes
這些變化的成分的這些參數
these parameters
這些參數
Then we can also get the predicted value of the surface acceleration
那我們也可以得到這個地表加速度的預測值
Bring these parameters into
把這些參數通通帶進
bring in
帶進去
then go get it
然後去得到它的
95% confidence interval or prediction interval
95%的信賴區間或者是預測區間
Just like the poll example just now
就像剛剛那個民意調查的例子一樣
We can construct its prediction interval
我們可以去建構它的預測的區間
so what
所以呢
we use this
我們用這個
period ratio
期間多比
this
這個
just these stations
剛剛這些測站
The resulting data
所得到的數據
In fact, most of these stations are operated by us
這個這些測站其實多數是由我們的
The Central Weather Service and this us
中央氣象局還有這個我們
Academia Sinica's Institute of Earth Sciences
中研院的地球科學研究所
they established
他們所設立的
so
所以
These are the earthquakes just mentioned
這些就是剛剛講過的那些地震
Those ones
那些
Those Effects
那些Effect
Those Earthquakes
那些Earthquake
those
那這些
These are those Sites those side stations
這些是那些Site 那些側站
so this is us
所以這個是我們
The previous regression model
前面的這個回歸的模型
M is the magnitude of the earthquake
M是這個地震的規模
R is the distance from this point to the center
R是這個地點跟這個正央的距離
So this is a common one for their earthquake engineering
所以這是他們地震工程學常用的一個
What the regression model looks like
回歸模型的樣子
Then we have to do more than just this regression model
那我們要做的不僅僅是這個回歸模型
what about us
我們另外呢
I also hope that this is the parameter value of this model
還希望這個就是這個模型的參數值
We use the EM algorithm
我們利用EM演算法
The resulting parameter value
所得到的參數值
and the one with its central limit theorem
以及它的中央極限定理的那個
the one with the normal distribution
常態分布的那個
that
那個
the width of that change
那個變化的寬度
Error that standard arrow
誤差那個standard arrow
that standard
那個標準物
good
好
that this is that
那這個是那個
just said
就剛剛講的
We have
我們有
different earthquakes
不同的地震
Caused change This parameter Amount of change
造成的變化 這個參數 變化量
The amount of variation caused by different locations
不同的地點 造成的變化量
Is there any way to explain it by all known causes
還有沒有辦法由所有已知的原因來解釋的
The remaining changes, these uncertainties
剩下的這些變化 這些不確定性
So is the estimate of the parameter of these parameters
所以是這些參數的 參數的估計值
the values ​​of the parameters and their
參數的值 還有他們的
The degree of variation produced by sampling error
抽樣誤差所產生的變化的程度
its standard
它的標準物
These are obtained by the EM algorithm
這些都是由EM演算法可以得到的
Then this, Vice President Zhou just said
那這個 剛剛周副院長有講
Can we have such a model to know
我們是不是可以有這樣的模型 可以知道
Which side is safer and which side is less safe, right?
在哪邊比較安全 在哪邊比較不安全 對不對
So this is an example that says
所以這就是一個例子就是說
Because we can get the effect of the location, right?
因為我們可以得到這個地點的影響 對不對
The impact of this site just now
剛剛這個Site它的影響
So here are some different tactics
所以這是一些不同的策戰
This is Yilan
這是宜蘭的
Hualien's Taipei's Kaohsiung's Yilan's
花蓮的 台北的 高雄的 宜蘭的
so you can see it's slightly safer in this place
所以你就可以看到 在這個地方稍微安全
A little bit because its surface acceleration will deduct a little bit
一點 因為它地表加速度會扣掉一點
right
對不對
This place will also deduct a little, then this place will add
這個地方也會扣掉一點 那這個地方會加
plus a little plus a little more than average
加上一點 加上一點 加上一點 比平均
just add a little bit, right?
只要加上一點 對不對
so this is
所以這個就是
Predict this surface acceleration from the location
根據地點來預測這個地表加速度的
An example is our original purpose
一個例子 也是我們當初的目的
At the beginning we just hoped that in
當初我們就是希望說 在
above the original regression model, can we go further
原始的回歸模型上面 我們可不可以進一步的
Pick out the effects of location Pick out the effects of earthquakes
把地點的影響挑出來 地震的影響挑出來
This way we can get more accurate predictions
這樣我們可以得到更精確的預測
Well, this one is based on different earthquakes
好 那這個是根據不同的地震
Pick out its effects and this one is
把它的影響挑出來 那這個就是
921 This Extremely Large Earthquake
921 這個極其大地震
Happened in 1999
發生在1999年的
The 921 earthquake
這個921大地震
So this is what I just explained
所以這種 這個就是我剛剛解釋
In fact, after you take the special factor of location into consideration
其實你把地點 這個特別的因素考慮進來以後呢
What if you use this EM algorithm to make a prediction?
你透過這個EM演算法 你來做一個預測的話呢
You are actually better than the original regression model they used that did not take into account the location.
你其實比原始他們用的那個 沒有考慮地點的那個回歸模型呢
When you construct its ninety-five stars to interval
你建構它的九十五星來區間的時候
Realization This diagram may not be clear
實現 這個圖可能不太清楚
Achieving this is its range
實現這個 是它的區間
You can see that for this strategy in Taipei
你可以看到 對於台北的這個策戰而言
Well, actually, it turns out that this didn’t take into account the location.
那其實這個 原來這個沒有考慮地點這個
What about the prediction interval at the 95-star level?
九十五星星水準的預測區間呢
doesn't cover ground acceleration at this location at all
根本沒有涵蓋住這個地點的地表加速度
Right, this range is here
對不對 這個區間在這裡
But it is not included in the strategy of Taipei
可是它 這個台北這個策戰 沒有被包含進來
is not covered by this prediction interval of the ninety-five
沒有被涵蓋在這個九十五的這個預測區間
But if you consider the site conditions of the station itself
但是如果你考慮了這個測站本身的這個地點條件的話
The interval you construct will be this dotted line
你建構的區間會是這個虛線
So you can see that it will better cover the surface acceleration of this location
所以你就可以看到它就會比較好的涵蓋住這個地點的這個地表加速度
The same is true for a station in Kaohsiung
同理對於這個高雄的一個測站也是一樣的
This location of this station is here
這個測站的這個位置在這裡
This its PGA surface acceleration is here
這個它的PGA地表加速度是在這裡
This is the 95% prediction interval constructed based on the characteristics of the site
這個是根據這個地點的特性所建構的95%預測區間
That realization is this interval
那實現是這個區間
Implementations also include live without taking into account
實現也有包含住沒有考慮
Those who did not consider the characteristics of this site are also included in the station in Kaohsiung
沒有考慮這個地點特性的也有包含在高雄這個測站
But its location is on the edge
可是它的位置就是在比較邊緣的地方
good
好
The EM algorithm just mentioned is a very general method
那剛剛講的EM演算法是一個非常general的方法
So in fact, this earthquake engineering expert
所以後來其實這個地震工程的專家
they hope that means
他們希望就是說
if my
如果我的
What if the effect of my earthquake is
如果我這個地震的效應呢 是
Just this model is
剛剛這個模型是
The effect of an earthquake is the same
地震的效應都是一樣的
all earthquakes
所有的地震
effect is the same
效應都是一樣
That
那
Earthquake engineers asked
地震工程學家就問了
Then if the effect of my earthquake will follow
那如果我的地震的效應會隨著
Will it be different in size?
它的規模會不一樣呢
I think this is a very reasonable question
我想這是一個很合理的問題
Then we can easily
那我們也很容易的可以
Take this EM algorithm slightly
把這個EM演算法稍微的
rewrite it
改寫一下
we can go and calculate
我們就可以去進行計算
Above is my first example
以上就是我的第一個例子
My first example to summarize
我的第一個例子做個總結
that is
就是說
Now we have very, very many in Taiwan
現在我們在臺灣已經有非常非常多
They now have a very
他們現在有非常 他們現在已經有一個數據庫了
have a database
有一個資料庫
So I think you can apply with them if you want to use it.
所以我想大家要用的話是可以跟他們申請的
That
那
In fact, the statistical regression has been
那其實一直以來統計的回歸
model approach has been used for this surface acceleration
模型的方法已經被用在這種地表加速度
The construction of the decay model
衰建模型的建構上面
From which to evaluate the so-called Size Mihaasang
從中去評估所謂的Size Mihaasang
earthquake risk
就是地震風險
But we can use more
那但是我們可以利用更
A more refined statistical model
精細一點的統計模型
For example, as shown here
例如像我這邊所呈現的這種
The so-called mixed-effects or random-effects model
所謂的混合效應或者是隨機效應模型
We can further take the original regression model inside
我們可以進一步的把原來回歸模型裡面的
What about the variable part?
變異的部分呢
Further according to different sources
進一步的依據不同的來源
different ingredients
不同的成分
For example from Earthquake itself
譬如說是來自 Earthquake 本身的
from Sight itself
跟來自 Sight 本身的
to further disassemble
去進一步的拆解
get more accurate forecasts
得到更精確的預測
statistical algorithm
統計的演算法
like 1M algorithm
像是 1M 演算法
can help us do this
可以去幫我們做到這件事情
Statistical Proxy Sample Theory
統計的代樣本理論
You can also help us further
也可以進一步的來幫助我們
Evaluate the resulting model on the data
評估數據所得到的模型
its error how much its uncertainty
它的誤差 它的不確定性有多少
So this is my first example
所以這是我的第一個例子
Thanks
謝謝
Well, the second example is to follow the popular big data
好 那第二個例子是為了要跟現在很流行的大數據
hope there is a little connection
希望能夠有一點關聯
So here's an example of integration of different databases
所以就舉了這個例子 不同資料庫的整合
Now because, a lot of databases, a lot of this database
現在因為呢 很多資料庫 很多這個數據庫
It's all there for everyone to use, whether it's a government agency.
都在那邊可以供大家使用 不管是政府機構的
or a private institution
或者是私人機構的
Slowly now because of the trend of big data, there may be more and more such data
慢慢現在因為是大數據的風潮 可能有越來越多這樣的數據
What about this data? Its advantage is that it is usually very large.
那這些數據呢 它的優點是呢 它通常量很大
A large amount because it can be very cumulative for very many people
量很大 因為它可能是非常累積非常多人
Daily life, for example, it is called UBIKE, right?
日常生活 譬如說它起UBIKE 對不對
Its records, or our health care records, our doctor's records
它的記錄 或者是我們健保 我們看病的記錄
so everyone
所以是所有人
A large amount of data accumulated for a long time every day
每天很長時間累積的一個大量數據
So its advantage is that it has a large amount
所以它的優勢是它的量很大
but on the other hand
但是另外一方面呢
It has the disadvantage that
它有這樣的缺點就是說
Because it wasn't meant for a real one
因為它當初並不是為了一個真正的一個
Collected for the purpose of measuring something in detail
想要精細量測什麼東西的目的去蒐集的
So what about its data?
所以它的資料呢
The quality may be rough
品質可能比較粗糙一點
There may be a lot of errors, right?
那可能會有很多的誤差對不對
what about the other
那另外呢
even
甚至呢
For example, like the health insurance database
比如說像健保資料庫
Anyone who has analyzed the health insurance database knows that
大家如果有分析健保資料庫的都知道
Actually because
其實因為
Currently because of
目前因為對於
The so-called capital
所謂的各資
so-called personal privacy
所謂的個人的隱私
is guaranteed
是有保障的
so
所以
you can't just say
你是不能夠直接的就是說
you can't get these
你是不能夠去取得這些
Although it has large data
雖然它有很大的數據
But you can't get its personal data
可是你是不能取得它的個人的資料
Our statistical analysis needs it for a long time
我們統計分析很長時候是需要它的
individual data personal data
individual data 個人的資料
One by one we can analyze
一條一條我們才可以分析
but now
但現在呢
it allows you to analyze
它可以讓你分析
But it doesn't let you take this profile back
但是它不能讓你把這個個人資料帶回去
You can only take the results of the analysis
你只能夠把分析的結果
That is, Somber is the taste is
也就是這個Somber is the taste is
These sufficient statistics bring back
這些充分統計量帶回去
Like the so-called we went to the Ministry of Health and Welfare
像我們到衛生福利部的所謂的
value-added center
這個加值中心
That's it
就是這樣
you can go in and sit at its computer
你可以進去坐在它的電腦
To analyze the health insurance database
去分析健保資料庫
but when you go
但是你走的時候
It can only bring out your analysis results
只能帶你的分析結果出來
You can't bring the data out
你是不能把資料帶出來的
good
好
but on the other hand
那但是另外一方面呢
A person or some may exist now
一個人或者是現在可能就現存著一些
existing some
現有的一些
For other databases it might be
另外的一些資料庫它可能是
There are finer
有比較精細的去
measured to some
測量到一些
the data you want
你想要的數據的
These databases may exist or
這些資料庫可能是存在的或者就是說
yourself if
你自己如果
If there is such a data to be collected
就有去收集這樣的資料的話
That's the kind of information you have on hand.
那也是你手邊就有的這樣的資料
right
對不對
So a natural question is to say
所以很自然的一個問題就是說
Here you have some very
這邊你有一些很
detailed measurement data
精細的測量的資料
But because it's finely measured
但是因為它很精細測量
so its amount
所以它的量
maybe not too big
可能就不能太大
right
對不對
because
因為
Fine measurements cost a lot of money
精細測量要花很多錢
right
對不對
you can't measure too many people
你不可能測量太多的人
too many people
太大量的人
So you have a profile like this
所以你有這樣的資料
is it possible to follow
那是不是可以跟
the one above
上面的這個
this huge database
這個很大的資料庫
it's big
它很大
a lot of it
對 它量很大
but a little rough
但是稍微粗糙一點
How can you combine these two
你怎麼樣可以把這兩種
database combined
資料庫結合起來
so this is us
所以這是我們
question to ask
要問的問題
Okay, so our motivation is to say
好 那我們的動機就是說
There is a doctor who has one at hand
是有個醫生他手邊有一個
National Health Interview Survey
所謂的國民健康訪問調查
That this is 2005
那這個是2005年
this is
這個是
National Institutes of Health in Taiwan
台灣的這個國家衛生研究院
and the National Health Service
還有國民健康署
what they
他們所
an interview survey
進行的一個訪問調查
This is a very detailed visit
這是很詳細的訪問了
More than 20,000 residents of Taiwan
兩萬多個台灣的居民
very carefully
很仔細的
Ask them what diseases they have
去問他們的有哪些疾病啊
and then include their diet
然後還有包括他們的飲食
their living habits
他們的生活習慣
their smoking and drinking
他們的抽菸喝酒
so
所以
There is such a database
有這樣的一個資料庫
This is a very detailed database
這是一個很詳細的資料庫
but this database
但是它這個資料庫
Relatively speaking, the amount is not that large
相對來說量沒有那麼大
That's all, more than 20,000 people
就是全部就是2萬多人
What the doctor wants to analyze is
那這個醫生想要分析的是
because he found
因為他發現
patients with herpes zoster
帶狀泡疹的患者
Herpes zoster I don't know everyone
帶狀泡疹我不知道大家
Do you know what kind of disease this is?
知不知道這是一種什麼樣的疾病
It's a disease of the immune system
這是一種免疫系統造成的疾病
he is in pain
他非常的痛
It's a sharp pain
非常痛
If you have this rash
你如果長這個泡疹
it will be very painful
會非常痛
you must see a doctor
你一定會去看醫生
will definitely see a doctor
一定會去看醫生
Then the doctor found
那這個醫生發現
Many people who get shingles with this shingles
這個帶狀泡疹得到帶狀泡疹的很多人
He also has COPD
他同時也有慢性阻塞性肺病
COPD
COPD
so he just watched
所以他就看
Are these two diseases related?
這兩個病是不是有關係
do you have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
是不是你有慢性阻塞性肺病的
prone to herpes zoster
就會容易得帶狀泡疹
that's in this
那在這個
If he wants to discuss such issues
如果他要討論這樣的問題的時候
he has a lot
他還有很多
Other variables to consider
其他的變數要考慮
for example
譬如說
There are a lot more
還有很多
other comorbidities
其他的共發疾病
comorbidity
共發疾病
such as high blood pressure, diabetes
比如說高血壓、糖尿病
These will be accompanied by both levels of water
這些都會伴水的這兩種級
together with the
並一起產生的
Then there is smoking and drinking
那另外還有就是抽菸跟喝酒
especially smoking
特別是抽菸
because
因為
Many people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease are
慢性阻塞性肺病的人很多是
Primers
引菌子
I mean smoke a lot
就是說抽很多菸的
It is easy for smokers to get
那抽菸的人呢也很容易會得到
Ribbon foam pillow
帶狀泡枕
so
所以
smoking is an important
抽菸是一個很重要的
this
這個
Factors that must be included in the analysis
必須要加入分析的因子
and drinking
還有喝酒
So these data can be found in
所以這些資料都可以在
National Health Survey in French
國民健康法文調查得到
This is a very detailed investigation
這是一個很詳細的調查
But it's not that big
但是它的量沒有那麼大
So the doctor thought
所以這個醫生就想
Then can I use the health insurance database?
那我可不可以利用健保資料庫
Because now the health insurance database
因為現在健保資料庫
very hot right now
現在非常熱門
The health insurance database is missing.
那健保資料庫就缺少了
smoking and drinking
抽菸跟喝酒
no smoking and drinking
沒有抽菸跟喝酒的
data
數據
how about
那怎麼樣
In this way, the health insurance database lacks smoking and drinking
這樣把健保資料庫缺少抽菸跟喝酒的
The result of such an analysis we call
這樣的分析結果 我們叫做
one reduce model one
一個reduce model 一個
A scaled down model because it's less smoking and less drinking, right?
一個縮減的一個模型 因為它少了抽菸跟喝酒 對不對
So what about the results? It’s the same as your National Health Interview Survey.
那這樣的結果怎麼樣 跟你國民健康訪問調查這個
fine this
精細的這個
results combined
結果結合起來
ok so here it is
好 所以這邊就是說
There are some
有一些
a little symbol
有一點點小小的符號
YX stands for Y
YX就是代表 Y
It's ours. This one we're going to see is
就是我們的 我們要看的這個是
Ribbon foam pillow
帶狀泡枕
X is
X就是
Do you have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and other comorbid diseases?
有沒有慢性阻塞性肺病 還有其他的共發疾病
But what we are talking about now is that the data is obtained from external data, which is the so-called health insurance database.
但是呢 我們現在講的是資料是從外部資料得到的 也就是所謂的健保資料庫
A large database gets
一個很大的數據庫得到的
So it's missing some other variables
所以它缺少了一些其他的變數
such as smoking and drinking
譬如說抽菸跟喝酒
that's okay
那沒有關係
We use this simplified model
我們就利用這個簡化的模型
reduced model
縮減的模型
we get a final
我們得到一個最後的
Summary
Summary
A Summary's TASY
一個Summary's TASY
Let's say Said
假設叫Said
That's because the health insurance database
那因為健保資料庫
Can't take its personal information directly
不能夠直接拿它的個人資料
So we can only use this Summary's TASY
所以我們只能夠用這個Summary's TASY
It describes the relationship between Y and X
它描述的是Y跟X的關係
Then it is more precise
再來就是比較精細的
Our name is Internal Data
我們叫Internal Data
In addition to Y and X
它除了有Y跟X之外
it also has z
它還有Z
some more details
一些更詳細的資料
such as smoking and drinking
譬如說抽菸跟喝酒
So if you analyze Y X Z
所以你如果分析Y X Z
integrated analysis
一體分析的話
A Summary of what you can get
你可以得到的一個Summary
Summary is Beta
Summary是Beta
Beta
Beta
The main purpose of statistical inference
統計推論的主要的目的
So how do we combine the two together?
那我們怎麼樣把這兩個結合在一起呢
How to combine beta and seta
beta跟seta怎麼樣結合在一起
One is the lack of some data
一個是缺少一部分資料
It is a summary of what we call the reduce model
它是一個我們叫reduce model的一個summary
One is the summary beta of the complete information
一個是完整資料的summary beta
How do these two fit together?
這兩個怎麼樣結合在一起呢
In fact, it is very simple, we just use the law of large numbers
其實很簡單我們就是利用大數法則
Because according to the law of large numbers
因為根據大數法則呢
This seta this summary statistic
這個seta這個summary statistic
it will approach this
它會趨近到這個
The real value of this group
這個群體的真正的值
And the real value of the group will be related to beta
而群體的真正的值會跟beta有關係
Because according to one of our probability theory
因為根據我們在機率論裡面的一個
The simplest formula is called total probability
最簡單的公式叫全機率
The law of total probability, right?
全機率定律對不對
The law of total probability tells us
全機率定律告訴我們
total probability tells us
total probability告訴我們
total probability is
total probability是
Conditional probability multiplied by marginal probability
條件機率乘上邊際機率
right
對不對
So we are based on this simple one
所以我們就是根據這個這麼簡單的一個
Law of Large Numbers and Total Product Rate
大數法則跟全積率
we can go build
我們就可以去建立
The relationship between β and θ
β跟θ之間的關係
So if you go through the health insurance database now
所以如果你現在透過健保資料庫
You already know the words θ
你已經知道θ的話
It represents β to some extent
就代表β某種程度
also satisfy a relationship history
也要滿足一個關係史
So at this time our statistical inference
所以這個時候我們的統計推論
We just wanted statistical inference
我們剛剛想統計推論
The pursuit of process optimization, right?
追求過程的最佳化對不對
So when we require the maximum value of the target content
所以我們要求目標含數的最大值的時候
We are no longer just the original maximum.
我們就不再只是原來的最大值而已了
We also add that because of the external data
我們還要加上因為外部資料
message to me
給我的訊息
a history of our relationship
我們有的一個關係史
So this is the use of
所以這樣就是利用到
We are in the Elementary Wikipedia
我們在初等維基分裡面
Learned method of Lockrange Multi-Prior
學到的Lockrange Multi-Prior的方法
that is, with restrictions
就是在有限制條件的情況下
Let us seek the optimization of an objective content
我們來求一個目標含數的最佳化
So we just use this simple trick
所以我們就是利用這種簡單的技巧
We can combine external data with internal data
我們可以把外部資料跟內部資料結合在一起
then we can also get
那我們一樣可以得到
The central limit theorem of such statistical inferences
這樣的統計推論的中央極限定理
That is, it varies with sampling
也就是說它隨著抽樣的變化
Its changes still obey a normal law
它的變化還是服從一個常態的規律
And the width of the normal and its variation
而且這個常態的寬度它的變異
can be calculated by the formula
是可以由公式算出來的
and we found
而且我們發現
The width of this normal distribution and its variation must be greater than
這個常態分布的寬度它的變異一定會比
Its error, the sampling error, must be greater than
它的誤差 抽樣的誤差一定會比
You only use your original Internal Data
你只用你原本的Internal Data來的小
So it means that you use these additional data
所以就代表說你用這些額外的資料
use these health care databases use these external data
用這些健保資料庫用這些外部的資料
is helpful
是有幫助的
It reduces your sampling error
它可以降低你的抽樣誤差
ok so
好 所以呢
Another one we can combine with internal data
另外一個我們可以結合內部數據
methods with external data
跟外部數據的方法
Also using the central limit theorem
也是利用中央極限定理
We use the bivariate normality relationship
我們利用二變量常態的關係
You can build this β and θ
可以去建立這個β跟θ
Remember that β is the parameter of our exact model
大家記得β是我們精確的模型的參數
θ is our external data
θ是我們外部資料的
Compare Simplify compares the parameters of the reduced model
比較簡化比較縮減的模型的參數
You use a central limit theorem
你利用一個中央極限定理
Using the relationship of bivariate normal distribution
利用二變量常態分布的關係
It is also possible to construct the relationship between these two parameters
也可以去建構這兩個參數之間的關係
This is also a way
這也是一種方法
You can combine internal data with external data
你可以去結合內部資料跟外部資料
so what
所以呢
finally
最後呢
What about the results of our analysis?
我們分析的結果呢
That's it
就是這樣
that is
就是說
If we only use the health insurance database
如果我們只用健保資料庫
This is a
這是一個
This analysis is a comparative
這個分析是一個比較
Simplified Analysis
比較簡化的分析
because he failed to take into account two important variables
因為他沒有考慮到兩個重要的變數
smoking and drinking
抽菸跟喝酒
So under such analysis
所以在這樣的分析之下
we got this code foam pillow
我們得到這個代狀泡枕
Relationship with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
跟慢性阻塞性肺病的關係
is 1.7
是1.7
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
That is to say, people who have foam pillows
就是說有代狀泡枕的人
he will get this later
他日後會得到這個
Patients with COPD
有慢性阻塞性肺病的病人
I've mispoken
說錯了
The risk that he will get a proxy pillow at a later date
他日後會得到代狀泡枕的風險
is without COPD
是沒有COPD
patients without chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
沒有慢性阻塞性肺病的病人的
1.7 times
1.7倍
That is, if you have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
也就是說你有慢性阻塞性肺病的話
you will have higher
你會有比較高的
risk to get this bandage
風險去得到這個帶狀炮癥
This multiple is 1.7 times
這個倍數是1.7倍
But what about such an analysis?
但是這樣的分析呢
is a rough analysis
是一個比較粗略的分析
Simplified Analysis
比較簡化的分析
because it's only based on the health insurance database
因為它只根據健保資料庫
There is no information about smoking and drinking
沒有抽菸跟喝酒的這個資料
So if you use the National Health Interview Survey
那如果你用國民健康訪問調查
it has all the data
它是有所有的資料的
But its data volume is relatively small
但是它的數據量比較小
Its Sumpo Size
它的Sumpo Size
Its sample size is relatively small
它的樣本數比較小
The result you get is something like this
你得到的結果是這樣子
what does it mean
是什麼意思呢
that is, chronic obstructive
就是說有慢性阻塞性
What about non-disease patients?
非病的病人呢
His risk of getting banding
他得到帶狀炮癥的風險
is not chronic obstructive
是沒有慢性阻塞性
2.83 times that of non-disease patients
非病病人的2.83倍
This risk increases
這個風險更增加了
But it should be noted that
可是要注意一下的就是說
its central limit theorem
它的中央極限定理的
The one in the normal distribution
這個常態分布裡面的那個
What about the smoking variant?
抽菸的那個變異呢
that width
那個寬度
Just imagine the normal width
你就想像那個常態的寬度呢
also quite big
也相當的大
This means that your result
這就代表就是說你這個結果呢
because your sample size
因為你的樣本數
Everyone remembers that it consumes 1/M more, right?
大家記得是更耗M分之一對不對
So your sample size is relatively small
所以你的樣本數比較小
so your error
所以你的誤差
Your sampling error will be relatively large
你的抽樣誤差會比較大
So 1.56
所以1.56
So even though you have such a big risk
所以造成雖然說你有這麼大的風險
But because your uncertainty is also great
可是因為你的不確定性也很大
So we have to calculate a ratio in the end
所以造成整個我們最後要算一個比值
This ratio is generally greater than 2
這個比值一般來說要大於2
We'd better do this significantly
我們才最好做這個顯著
That is to say, the p value is small
也就是說p value是小
The p value just mentioned
剛剛講的p value
be less than 0.05
要小於0.05
So what is the current ratio?
所以現在的這樣的比值呢
That is to say its statistic itself
就是說它的統計量本身
the estimator itself compared to its uncertainty
估計量本身比上它的不確定性
Compared with its stand arrow
比上它的這個stand arrow
This ratio does not exceed 2
這個比值並沒有超過2
So its result is not significant enough
所以它的結果還不夠顯著
so i can't draw any firm conclusions
所以我沒有辦法下任何肯定的結論
But if you use the two
但是如果你用這剛講的兩種
This combination of internal and external data
這種同時結合內部資料跟外部資料的
Combining health insurance database with
結合健保資料庫跟
The data from the National Health Interview Survey
這個國民健康訪問調查的資料
The result you get is this
你得到的結果是這樣的
this
這個
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease causes
慢性阻塞性肺病造成
Risks of Ribbon Pillows
帶狀泡枕的風險
This multiple is almost 1.9 times
這個倍數差不多是1.9倍
but its this
但是它的這個
sampling error
抽樣的誤差
Everyone remembers the one with the normal distribution
大家記得那個常態分布的那個
that width that error
那個寬度那個誤差
also dropped to only 0.11
也降到只有0.11
Only a tenth of the original size is smaller
只是原來的十分之一還要小
so what
所以呢
This will make your
這樣就會讓你的這個
pen value
筆值呢
your
你的
Estimated value divided by its standarrow pen value
估計值除上它的standarrow這個筆值呢
yes
是
more than 10
超過10的
so it's very, very significant
所以是非常非常顯著的
So its p-value is 0.05
所以它的p value是0.05
So this illustrates this
所以這就說明了這個
you combine
你結合
External materials
外部資料
analysis is helpful
分析是有幫助的
can reduce your sampling error
可以降低你的這個抽樣的誤差
I think I'll just use these two examples
我想我就用這兩個例子
with everyone
跟大家
explain
解釋一下
what i do
我所做的東西
that's statistics
那這是統計學
doing something
在做些什麼東西
Of course, this is just my personal one-sided
當然這只是我個人的一些片面的
very one-sided things
非常片面的一些東西
Let's see if you have any questions
接下來看大家有沒有什麼問題
ok thank you
好 那謝謝
Some of Mr. Chen's
陳老師的一些
made a with us
跟我們做了一個
equal to an overview
等於是一個概觀
for this statistical
對於這個統計學
some things you can do
能做的一些事情
that's how we are now
那我們現在是這樣子
Our organizers are ready
我們主辦單位有準備了
scientific magazine
科學人雜誌
There are
這邊有
There are about 10 copies, so every guest who asks a question
大概有10本 所以每一位發問的來賓
can get 1 copy
都可以得到1本
So we can start from this sequence of questions
所以我們可以從這個發問的次序
We will be giving away this hope to finish the 10 copies
我們會把這個希望能把這個10本給送完
Okay, is there anyone in the audience right now?
好 那現在有沒有哪一位聽眾
this way first thank you
這邊先來 謝謝
Hello, Mr. Chong, let me ask you about the application examples behind you
崇老師您好 跟您請教一下關於您後面的應用例子
In the approach of ground acceleration for earthquake engineering
在做地震工程的地表加速度的那個approach裡面
Is your R the epicenter or the epicenter? I’m just curious.
您那個R是震央還是震遠 我只是好奇
this is the first little problem
這是第一個小問題
The second part is whether there is a way to do anti-authentication
第二個部分是有沒有辦法去做反驗證
For example, Taipei City is in the side-to-side valuation
譬如說台北市的在那個side to side的那個valuation裡面
Is it relatively larger
是不是相對會比較大
Because everyone in Taipei knows that there is a formation amplification effect
因為台北大家都知道有一個地層放大效應
Is it possible to improve the reliability and validity?
那有沒有可能去做這個信度效度上的提升
and then go further to give feedback
然後進一步去做反饋
your original model
您那個原來的model
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, I think this R should refer to
對 我想這個R應該是指
Did you just ask about politics?
你剛剛是問政樣嘛
It's still Zhengyuan, right?
還是政源對不對
because you just said politics
因為你剛剛說政樣
So I'm curious to say
所以我很好奇是說
Why not Zhengyuan
為什麼不是政源
Zhengyuan is the real legend drama
政源才是真正的傳說劇集嘛
this is normal
這是正常的
Yes, it is actually divided into two dramas
對 它其實有分兩種劇裡
Actually, I'm not very clear about the details.
其實這個詳細我並不是分得很清楚
one should be what you mean
一個應該就是你指的
Just the picture I just had
就我剛剛那個圖
that is to say it has
就是說它有
when they define the play
他們在定義這個劇裡的時候
There are indeed some differences
的確是有一些不同的
defined method
定義的方法
that one is political
那有一個是政樣
One possibility is the political source you mentioned
有一個可能就是你講的政源
So both are used
所以這兩個都有人用
right
對
The second point is that
那第二點就是說
what you just said is
你剛剛講的就是說
If according to the characteristics of this address
如果依據這個地址的特性
For example, what is pious or something?
譬如說什麼虔誠還是什麼的
Can I get it from here again?
那可不可以從這邊再得到
I think that's what we're here for
我想這就是我們的目的
That is to say, to take the characteristics of this place
就是說要把這個地點的特性
want
要
access to our forecast
進入到我們的預測
You can get some more precise analysis
你可以得到一些更精確的分析
right
對
Then you say in this from
那你說在這個從中
What about getting some corrections
在得到一些校正什麼
i think it is
我想就是
In order to get more accurate predictions
為了要得到更精確的預測
right
對
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Everyone, the next one
各位 下面一位
Teacher Chen
陳老師
i have two questions
我有兩個問題
The first question is to say
第一個問題是說
when you're predicting low
當你在預測低症的時候
you have already happened
你是已經發生了
So you collect a lot of data
所以你去收取很多資料
for analysis
來做分析
So can you predict
那你有沒有辦法預測出
Who did he say would happen
他哪個說要發生
There is a second question
還有第二個問題是說
in case he happens
萬一他發生的時候
you know where he is
你知道他正央在哪裡
but can you predict
可是你能不能預測
How far can he go
他的範圍能夠多大
range of influence
影響的範圍
Yes, then I have to type these two questions
對 那我必須要打這兩個問題
i didn't do it
我都沒有做
Yes because there may be some
對 因為可能有一些人
doing such a problem
在做這樣的問題
For example, predict
譬如說預測
when hypoxia occurs
低症何時發生
Then
然後
Also, his positive wave
還有就是說他的這個正波
maybe
可能會
How far does it radiate
輻射到多遠的地方
But I must say I have no experience with either of these
可是我必須說這兩個我都沒有經驗
because
因為
that is
就是說
The earthquakes I have come into contact with are all biased
我所接觸到的地震都是比較偏向
so-called earthquake engineering
所謂的地震工程
as you just said
就您剛剛講的就是說
an earthquake that has occurred
是已經發生的地震
then we go from it
那我們從它那邊
and look at its acceleration against the ground
然後看看它對地表加速度
and its impact on buildings
以及對建築物的影響
what we studied
那我們研究的
I didn't come across some
我並沒有接觸到一些
Possibly study some of the earthquake itself
可能研究一些地震本身的
some scientific nature
一些科學的性質啊
when will it happen
它什麼時候會發生
And then how does its shock wave propagate
然後它的震波是如何傳播
I don't have that
這一方面我是沒有
no contact
沒有接觸過
right
對
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
the third one is here
那第三位在這邊
Wait a moment
等一下
Hello Mr. Chen
陳老師好
Here
在這邊
Where
在哪裡
good
好
sorry
對不起
sorry sorry
不好意思不好意思
like this
是這樣子
because i saw you doing this earthquake
因為我我看到你做這個地震的這個
this model
這個模型
That's because I just happened to be a while ago
那因為我只是剛好前一陣子
We just had the sudden thought of saying
我們就是有突然間想到說
Let's just use that
那我們乾脆用那個
Low power consumption unlimited power and that
低功耗無限電還有那個
the chipped one
晶片化的那個
Accelerometer
加速度計
It's a six-axis accelerometer
就是六軸的加速度計
to put in some fixed position
去放在固定的一些位置上
Then it becomes a lot of distribution points
然後變成很多的分布點
This will form a sensor network
這樣就會形成一個感測網
and then to sense those points above
然後來感測那些點上面的
The vibrating Megane2
振動的那個Megane2
The strength of its government, etc.
那個它政府的強弱等等的
But so I see say this
但是所以我看到說這個
Mr. Chen, you are here
陳老師你這上面
I have done a lot of information on this
做了不少這方面的資料
It should be ten years, right?
應該有十幾年了嘛對不對
your sensor
你們那個感測器
Because the main thing is your sensor
因為最主要是說你那感測器
You still have the value it returns later
你還有它回傳以後的數值
your values
你那些數值
Mainly how can you be sure to say
你主要是怎麼樣能夠確定說
its values ​​are believable
它那些數值是可信的
Because if you say that you use the accelerometer to judge
因為你如果說這樣用加速度計來判斷的話
In fact, there will be a big problem, that is,
其實會有一個很大的問題就是說
Not necessarily an earthquake
不一定真的是地震
Maybe it's just a landslide today
搞不好說他今天只是個土石流而已
Or maybe there is a project nearby
或是說剛好附近有工程
Big trucks drive by and he still vibrates
大卡車開過去 他還是會震動
Under such circumstances, Mr. Chen, your materials
那像這樣的情況之下 陳老師你們這些資料
Have you done this kind of filtering such as reliability and so on?
有沒有去做這種信度上等等那種過濾的
In fact, they originally said that the data
其實他們當初這些數據就說
They received confirmation in this database
他們收到這個資料庫裡面都是有確認
he is an earthquake
他是一個地震
Because every time an earthquake occurs, the Central Meteorological Bureau will announce
因為每次發生地震一定中央氣象局會公佈
So sure it's an earthquake
所以確定這是一個地震
Right, so they're all sure
對不對 所以他們都是確定了
These surface accelerations from this earthquake
是這個地震所產生的這些地表加速度
they will be included in this database
他們才會納入到這個資料庫
So if what you just said is some other landslide
所以你剛剛講的如果是別的什麼土石流
Or a big truck has been driven
或者是大卡車開過啊
Or the MRT has been opened, the high-speed rail has been opened
或是捷運開過啊 高鐵開過啊
Then they should not be included in this earthquake
那他們應該是不會納入到這個地震
included, so they have to do some manual judgment
納入 所以他們是有做人工的一些判斷
to themselves and then snap out some unnecessary parts
對 他們自己 再把它卡掉一些不要的部分
Yes, when they were building this database
對 他們在建這個資料庫的時候
should do this
應該就做這件事情
OK OK OK
OK OK OK
Right, well, what about your accelerometer itself?
對 好 那你們那個加速度計本身來講的話
Are there any problems that need to be corrected?
有沒有說需要校正的問題
Because of this when we actually do
因為這個我們實際去做的時候
This problem happened, it seems to have heard them talking
就有發生這問題 好像有聽到他們在講
But this is not our specialty.
不過這個就不是我們統計的專業了
then they seem to have listened
那他們好像有聽
as if i heard them say
好像我有聽到他們講
they need to do some corrections or something
他們需要做一些什麼校正之類的
Yes, assuming the information they provide should be
對 假設他們供給的資料應該是
it's right it's right
是對的就對了
A certain design is correct from which statistical analysis
某一個設計正確可以從那一座統計分析
Yeah
對 對 對
The one behind just now, and the one who waits a little longer
那剛剛後面那位 然後再等一下那位好
just a little bit of advice
請教一點就是說
That is to say, in statistics
就是說在統計上面
part that is said to be man-made
屬於說是人為的部分
It's like talking about earthquakes when I was studying in high school
像說地震在以前高中讀書的時候
It's some water currents hitting plates.
是一些水流跟板塊衝擊啊
But if say, hypothesis says need experiment say
但是如果說 假設說需要實驗說
is it security
是不是它是安全性
How shockproof is it?
那它的防震程度
that might be
那可能就是
Bo Jun's bomb is under the ground
博軍的炸彈在地面下
Explosion at the bottom of the sea
在海底的爆炸
The kind of vibration that spread out in Taiwan
那種展身了台灣的震動
it's also possible
這也是可能的
that or
那或者是說
for some military precautions
做於一些軍事的防備
or experiment
或是實驗
such data
像這種數據的話
how to include
怎麼去納入
That and the gentleman just said
那以及剛剛那位先生說
If it is possible to do so
如果是可以這樣來
If the operation experiment
操作實驗的話
Is it possible to predict
那是不是也可以去預測說
Naturally occurring and man-made situations
自然發生跟人為發生的狀況
because why is it so small
因為為什麼會這麼小
Because I often spend three thousand midnight
因為我常常三千半夜
half done washing
洗東西洗完一半
Why another earthquake
怎麼又地震
that's too often
那太頻繁
I feel that it is the same as the theory of studying in high school before
覺得跟以前高中讀書的理論
a little weird
有一點怪怪的
so i want to say
所以我想說
Is it an artificial perception
它是不是有人為因素的看法
i want them this
我想他們這個
as long as i just said
只要我剛剛講過
That is to say, they should just consider
就是說他們應該就是只考慮
caused by the earthquake
因為地震所造成的
surface acceleration
地表加速度
they don't think about it
他們不會去考慮這個
what you just said
你剛剛講的
human factors
人為的因素
let's add
我們幾個補充一下
The man for the nuclear bomb test
那個人為了核彈實驗
Will he form energy dollars
他會不會形成能量上的美金
Then the shares I form are
然後我形成的股位就是
I don't know
這我就不知道了
Because I do not know
因為我不知道
I don't know if Taiwan is still conducting nuclear tests
我不知道台灣現在還有進行核試驗嗎
this
這個
I think this chance should be less
我想這個機會應該比較少吧
Of course, if it's from North Korea or somewhere else
那當然如果是北韓或是哪裡的
then i don't know
那我不知道
Does the region have this
區域是否有這個
Yes but this
對 但是這個都
i think both
我想都
none of them will appear again
他們都不會再出現在
The one we are analyzing now
我們現在分析的這個
In the so-called surface acceleration data of earthquakes
所謂地震的地表加速度的資料裡面
In other words, statistics and computers
就是說統計學還有電腦電腦電腦
Our statistics mean
我們統計學就是說
we see our purpose
我們看我們的目的
Our purpose is only to analyze earthquakes
我們目的只是要分析地震
right
對
Hello
喂
right here
對 這邊
Just learned that thread
剛剛學到那個線寶
When you say that thread treasure is very much needed
當你說那個線寶是要很需要
Which means he had the opportunity to study the life of this individual
就是說他有機會去研究這個個人的生命
But health insurance can solve personal life
但是健保他能夠解決個人的生命
on top of the male
在雄子上面
other human life
他人類的生命
After continuing to study
繼續研究以後
When an old man comes and goes, he still holds
當個老人自來自來還持有
The person who holds this condition
這個持有的人這種狀況
will
就會
In other words, the impact on the whole
也就是說對整體他的影響
Then we are now in Taiwan
那我們現在台灣
The former health team leader Yang Zhiqiang also said
去楊志強前衛生組長還講
Planetary aging in Taiwan
在台灣行星高齡化
2.82 million
兩百八十二萬
in this situation
像這種狀況的話
Our Mr. Fu Daren
我們那個傅達仁先生
poor kiln lady
窮窯女士
If they are like this
他們這種現象的話
This angle is accumulating
這個角度在累積
Cumulative to zero rigid angle
累積到零剛角
at best
最好的狀況之下
what do we do
我們要採取什麼行動
to solve the problem
來解決的問題
For example, the Anning Project
譬如說安寧專案
Is it going to pass
是不是要通過
Is this the case in Taiwan?
台灣是不是會有這種現象
That is to say, I want to ask you to say
就是說我要請教你說
between you personally and collectively
你個人和總體之間
place to take
要採取的地方
I think this is probably what people in their health policy have to consider
我想這個大概就是他們衛生政策的人要考慮的問題
Then the only thing statistics can do is to provide them with some real-world data.
然後門統計學做的只能就是說提供給他們一些現實當中的數據
right
對不對
Then as you just said, prolonging personal life or
然後就像您剛剛講的在延長個人生命或者是
For the whole country and society because of the senile dementia you just mentioned
那對於整個國家社會因為你剛剛講的老年持代症這些
How to balance the diseases of aging
老年化的疾病這個怎麼平衡
I think their health policy will make policy based on our data
我想他們衛生政策會根據我們的數據去做出政策的依據
right
對
good
好
learn
了解
There are often problems with missing children
常常會遇到一些缺子的問題
For example, we are distinguishing between healthy people and
比如說我們在區別健康的人跟
sick person that
得病的人 那
When doing grouping, there are some missing children, so there are some statistics
在做分群的時候遇到缺子 那有些統計
If the method encounters a shortage, he can only use this
方法遇到缺子他就只能把這
Sampo sacrificed him
SAMPO把他犧牲掉
But we are not willing to sacrifice too much SAMPO
但我們又不願意犧牲太多的SAMPO
Because sometimes it is not easy to obtain, so is there a time like this?
因為取得有時候很不容易 那這種時候有沒有
Some ways to overcome these problems
一些方法可以來克服這些問題
Yes, very, very much, yes, like what I just said
對 非常非常多 對 那像剛剛講的
EM algorithm is very suitable
EM演算法就是非常合適的
because what I just said
因為剛剛講的
The EM algorithm says
那個EM演算法就是說
Some parts of your model can be without
你的模型裡面可以有一部分是沒有
I see, the deficiency you just mentioned means there is no
看到的 那你剛剛講的缺子就是沒有
You see it, right?
看到了嘛 對不對
So you're in the EM algorithm
所以你在EM演算法裡面的
What about the first step? You can put the
一那個步驟呢 你就是可以把沒有
The part seen finds a way to use a reasonable
看到的部分想辦法用一個合理的
This missing piece will replace it, right?
這個缺子去代替 對不對
Then go get a reasonable
然後去得到一個這個合理的
Yes, there are many other ways
對 那還有很多其他的方法
that is to say in this
就是說在這個
The lack of fat you just mentioned, the loss of fat?
你剛剛講的缺脂缺失脂嘛
This is the focus of statistics and a study of statistics
這個是統計也是統計學的一個研究的重點
right
對
So I think you should be able to find this kind of method easily
所以我想你應該很容易可以找到這一類的方法
Okay, we have two questions here.
好 我們這邊有兩位有兩個問題
First off, I'm sorry
這位先 對不起啊
Literary advice means when you
文學建議就是說當你這個
A little more information about medicine
醫學上你多一點資訊
When you have more information and more information about smoking and drinking
你多一點資訊 多的抽菸喝酒的訊息的時候
in the whole model
在整個模特兒裡面
When you have some other relevant and useful information
當你多了一些其他的相關的有用的訊息
With this strip pillow and this lung condition
跟這個帶狀泡枕和這個肺病的狀況
Then you probably shouldn't increase
那麼你可能不應該增加
Because of the added information
因為增加了資訊
So you probably shouldn't increase
所以你可能不應該增加
That is to say, foam pillows affect lung diseases.
就是說像泡枕影響肺病的這個
this variation
這個 variation
In fact you are lowered Virgin much lower
事實上你是降低的Virgin降低很多
but here's the problem
但是這問題在這兒
I kind of disagree with your Standard Arrow
我有點不太贊成你那Standard Arrow
able to lower that much
能夠降低那麼多
It is because when you have a lot of information
是因為當你Information多的時候
does not represent a change in your main parameter
並不代表你的主要參數的變化
should be bigger
應該更大
so i have a little doubt
所以我有一點懷疑
Against my decades of statistical experience
Against我幾十年來的統計經驗
so i don't quite agree
所以我不太同意
That change can be so dramatic
那個變化可以那麼顯著
This is the first point
這是第一點
Second, if you have earthquake data
第二個如果你地震的資料
when your different site
當你不同的Site
in different intensities
在不同的強度
I suggest you take another factor into consideration
我建議你再考慮另外一個因素
That is to say, you travel from Zheng Yuan to Taipei City
就是說你從鄭園到台北市
When you go to different places in Kaohsiung
到高雄到不同的地點的時候
It this Pass
它這個Pass
It has different Pass
它有不同的Pass
Where the Pass passes
Pass經過的地方
that average change
那個平均變化
That change can probably be described a little bit
那個變化可能可以稍微描述一下
Describe the change of that Pass
刻畫一下那個Pass的變化
very important
影響蠻重要的
OK
OK
right
對
so i suggest you first
所以我先建議你這樣
Thank you very very much Mr. Chen
非常非常感謝你那個陳老師的
And Mr. Chen is a very experienced
以及陳老師是一位非常資深的
The lifted statistician
這個解除的統計學家
I was taken aback by the question he just asked
他剛剛發問我嚇了一大跳
right
對
first question
第一個問題
that is to say, i admit that is to say
就是說的確我承認就是說
We do this for different databases
我們做這個不同資料庫的
combine
結合
Companation actually requires some assumptions
companation其實是需要一些假設
how is your result
你的結果怎麼樣
to some extent
某種程度就是說
will be influenced by your assumptions
會受你的假設的影響
Then of course we are here
那我們這邊當然
because our assumptions about our assumptions
因為我們的假設關於我們假設
These two databases
這兩個資料庫
The material it contains is quite homogenous
它包含的資料是相當 homogenous
So that is to say, such a combibe
所以就是說這樣一combibe起來
like a lot
就好非常多
Especially as big as the health insurance database
尤其像健保資料庫那麼大
as soon as you bring it in
你一把它拿進來的時候
can force a lot
就可以影迫非常多
But I fully admit that
但是我完全承認就是說
totally agree that is to say
完全同意就是說
This is of course an assumption that
這當然是一個假設就是說
Assuming the two databases
假設這兩個資料庫
National Health Insurance Database and National Health Interview
健保資料庫跟國民健康訪問
very homogenous
非常 homogenous
Like Teacher Chen just said
像陳老師剛剛的意思就是說
Actually, I think what you mean is to say
其實我覺得您的意思應該就是說
In fact, if the two are different
其實如果這兩個是不同的
It's a bit different population, right?
是有點不太一樣的 population 對不對
So their own parameter values
所以他們的本身的參數值
maybe it's different
可能就不太一樣了
he himself will have a variation
他本身會有一個 variation
so you bring it in
所以你再把它納進來
May instead increase variation
可能反而是增加 variation
not reduce information
不是降低 information
then i totally agree
那我是完全同意
it is possible
是有這個可能的
But this means that it needs to be considered
但是這個就是說需要考慮
another model
另外一種模型
For example, mature model or something
譬如說mature model 或什麼的
Then consider the question
然後來考慮這樣的問題
That is, if we want to combine
就是說如果我們要 combine 的
are two very different populations
是兩個非常不一樣的 population
how would that be
那會是怎麼樣的情況
ok then your second question
好 那您的第二個問題
Actually I just skipped it
其實我剛剛略其
I didn't talk about it, I just said it. In fact, we were here later.
沒有講就是說 其實我們後來在這個
This regression model of this
這個回歸模型的這個
It's Fariousion's this
它的Fariousion的這個
As for the dismantling, we actually considered it later.
這個拆解上面呢 我們其實後來也考慮了
You just talked about the problem of this Pass
您剛剛講了這個Pass的問題
We have also considered the issue of Pass
這個Pass的問題 我們也考慮了
It is different Effects for different side stations
就是不同的Effect 對不同的側站
The impact of its Pass
它的Pass的影響
So this will make this
所以這個會讓這個
will make this
會讓這個
The prediction error will be further reduced
這個預測的誤差呢 會在進一步的減小
teacher long time no see
老師好久不見
Yes, long time no see. It's my master student.
對 很久不見 它是我的碩士學生
right
對
I just heard the teacher mention the total probability theorem
那個我剛剛聽到老師有提到全機率定理
theorem it can be integrated
定理它可以去整合
right
對
Integrate data from different databases
整合不同資料庫的資料
For example, when some databases are very large
比如說一些資料庫很龐大的時候
Information about my different consultations every day
我每天不同會診的資料
and then restore it
然後再把它還原
Then combine them to get a more accurate number
然後去結合算出一個比較精確的數字
Just upgrade that database
就是提升那個資料庫
The computational efficiency looks like this
在運算上的效率這樣子
Your question is about using the full chance
你的問題是說利用全機率
Can improve the efficiency of operation
可以提升運算的效率
Yes, we didn't actually consider
對 我們這邊其實沒有考慮到
Operational efficiency
運算效率
Our side is actually
我們這邊其實就是
think of a way
要想一個方法吧
Link internal data with external data
內部資料跟外部資料連在一起
So just use the law of large numbers
所以只是用個大數法則
Then use the formula of total probability
然後再利用全機率這個公式
that's all
就這樣而已
so
所以
Actually I feel like
其實我是覺得好像
as if he could
好像其實他可以
past database
可以以往資料庫
When improving operational efficiency
在提升運算效率的時候
It's all about hardware or
都是靠硬體或者是
write programs to improve
寫程式來提升
But today I heard full of special thoughts saying
可是我今天聽到滿特別的想法是說
He can use some statistical theorems
他可以用一些統計學的定理
Then to improve his computing efficiency
然後來提升他的運算上的效率
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
Okay, let's talk in private, yeah
好 我們私下再聊好了 對
And here are two more. The last two.
還有這邊還有兩位 最後兩位
Hello teacher, may I ask
老師好 請問一下
Although the EM algorithm can improve the maximization of our target cold accommodation
EM演算法它雖然可以提高我們目標寒宿的最大化
with optimization, but it sometimes has its drawbacks
跟最佳化 但是它有時候 它的缺點有時候會
The calculation is complex and the convergence rate is relatively slow, and it will depend on the cold weather of the initial parameters
計算複雜 而且收斂位比較慢 並會依賴初始參數的寒宿
For reference, the part in E-STEP will not affect us
去做參考 那在E-STEP的部分 是不會影響到我們
The strength of the interval so far, thank you
到現在區間的強度 謝謝
What you just said is absolutely correct, that is, the E-EM algorithm has a
你剛剛講的完全正確就是說 E-EM演算法它有一個
There are some disadvantages, for example, the biggest disadvantage is its
有一些缺點 譬如說最大一個缺點是它的
The operation speed is slower because
運算速度比較慢 因為
Right, because it's an algorithm we call linear
對 因為它是一個我們叫線性的演算法
it is slower
它是比較慢的
But what you just said is that
但是你剛剛講的就是說
E-EM algorithm
E-EM演算法
your final question is
你最後的問題是
That is to say, we have to rely on his initial parameters
就是說我們必須要依賴他的初始參數
make assumptions
去做假設嘛
Will this affect our ability to get
那這樣會不會影響到我們得到
The strength of the newcomer interval
新來區間的這個強度
yes yes yes you mentioned the new range
對對對您提到新來區間
What about the new range?
對那新來區間這個問題呢是
I don't think it matters, that is to say
我覺得是沒有關係的就是說
If once you're sure he's
如果你一旦確定他是
Convergent at last
最後是收斂的
Then finally you can use
那最後你就是可以用
We have this formula
我們有這個公式
We have this certain formula
我們有這個一定的公式
It can be used to calculate his newcomer range
是可以來計算他的新來區間的
so there is no problem
所以這是沒有任何問題的
right
對
should be
應該會吧
I know this video will be there
我知道這個錄影是都會在上面
PTT if the teacher is willing
PTT如果老師願意的話
The Folklore Department should be able to
民俗處應該可以
can handle
可以處理
nod over there
那邊再點頭
good
好
no problem
好 沒問題
Well, if we have
好 那如果說我們已經
Send out all the magazines
把那個所有的雜誌都發完了
before ending today's speech
那在結束今天的演講之前
I want to make a preview before the event
活動之前我想先做一個預告
Our next month is May
我們下個月就是5月份
The Feast of Knowledge is on May 29th
知識饗宴是在5月29號
by our Institute of Biochemistry
是由我們的生物化學研究所
This topic is completely different
這個題目完全不一樣
Is Wu Shixiong Distinguished Researcher
是吳世雄特聘研究員
So here in the life sciences group
所以在生命科學組這邊
The topic of his lecture is
他主講的題目是
The relationship between sugar molecules and life
糖質分子與生命的關係
So this is from our life science group
所以這個是我們生命科學組的
a speech
一個演講
Here we would like to thank our keynote speaker today
那在此我們要特別感謝我們今天的主講人
Teacher Chen
陳老師
Teacher Chen Yihao
陳一浩老師
Thanks
謝謝
give us a
給我們一個
thank you all
謝謝大家
yes
對啊
very special speech
很特別的演講
Then thank you all the guests
那也要謝謝各位來賓
again
再次
We hope to see you all again next month
我們希望下個月再看到大家
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝